<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Darwin, C. R. 1859. On the origin of species by means of natural selection, or the preservation of favoured races in the struggle for life. London: John Murray. 1st edition.</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher n="1">Institute for Textual Scholarship and Electronic Editing, Birmigham</publisher><date>Birmingham UK, 2009</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Prepared to accompany the distribution of the Anastasia system</p>
<p>See further: <xref>http://www.sd-editions.com/anastasia</xref></p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
 <change>Text prepared by John van Wyhe and Sue Asscher 2002, advertizements added
9.2006. Scanned by van Wyhe. Proofread and corrected by Asscher 8.2008. RN6</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="book">
<head>The first three chapters of the 1859 edition of Charles Darwin's 'On the Origin of Species'</head>
<pb id="S-7-1859" corres="E-7-1859" n="7"/><note type="pg"> 7 </note> <note type="rh"> CHAP. I. VARIATION UNDER DOMESTICATION. </note>
<div type="chapter"  n="CH1" >
<ab  n="T" id="CH1-T-1859">CHAPTER I. </ab>
<ab  n="ST" id="CH1-ST-1859">VARIATION UNDER DOMESTICATION.  </ab>
<ab  n="SQ" id="CH1-SQ-1859">Causes of Variability -- Effects of Habit -- Correlation of Growth -- Inheritance -- Character of Domestic Varieties -- Difficulty of distinguishing between Varieties and Species -- Origin of Domestic Varieties from one or more Species -- Domestic Pigeons, their Differences and Origin -- Principle of Selection anciently followed, its Effects -- Methodical and Unconscious Selection -- Unknown Origin of our Domestic Productions -- Circumstances favourable to Man's power of Selection. </ab>
<p  n="100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-100-100-1859">WHEN we look to the individuals of the same variety or sub-variety of our older cultivated plants and animals, one of the first points which strikes us, is, that they generally differ much more from each other, than do the individuals of any one species or variety in a state of nature. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-100-200-1859">When we reflect on the vast diversity of the plants and animals which have been cultivated, and which have varied during all ages under the most different climates and treatment, I think we are driven to conclude that this greater variability is simply due to our domestic productions having been raised under conditions of life not so uniform as, and somewhat different from, those to which the parent-species have been exposed under nature. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-100-300-1859">There is, also, I think, some probability in the view propounded by Andrew Knight, that this variability may be partly connected with excess of food. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-100-400-1859">It seems pretty clear that organic beings must be exposed during several generations to the new conditions of life to cause any appreciable amount of variation; and that when the organisation has once begun to vary, it generally continues to vary for many generations. <note type="rh">VARIATION CHAP. I.</note>  
 <pb id="E-7-1859" corres="S-7-1859" n="7"/>
<pb id="S-8-1859" corres="E-8-1859" n="8"/><note type="pg"> 8</note>  </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-100-500-1859">No case is on record of a variable being ceasing to be variable under cultivation. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-100-600-1859">Our oldest cultivated plants, such as wheat, still often yield new varieties: our oldest domesticated animals are still capable of rapid improvement or modification. </ab></p>
<p  n="200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-200-100-1859">It has been disputed at what period of life the causes of variability, whatever they may be, generally act; whether during the early or late period of development of the embryo, or at the instant of conception. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-200-200-1859">Geoffroy St. Hilaire's experiments show that unnatural treatment of the embryo causes monstrosities; and monstrosities cannot be separated by any clear line of distinction from mere variations. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-200-300-1859">But I am strongly inclined to suspect that the most frequent cause of variability may be attributed to the male and female reproductive elements having been affected prior to the act of conception. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-200-400-1859">Several reasons make me believe in this; but the chief one is the remarkable effect which confinement or cultivation has on the functions of the reproductive system; this system appearing to be far more susceptible than any other part of the organisation, to the action of any change in the conditions of life. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-200-500-1859">Nothing is more easy than to tame an animal, and few things more difficult than to get it to breed freely under confinement, even in the many cases when the male and female unite. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-200-600-1859">How many animals there are which will not breed, though living long under not very close confinement in their native country! </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-200-700-1859">This is generally attributed to vitiated instincts; but how many cultivated plants display the utmost vigour, and yet rarely or never seed! </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-200-800-1859">In some few such cases it has been found out that very trifling changes, such as a little more or less water at some particular period of growth, will determine whether or not the plant sets a seed. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-200-900-1859">I cannot here enter on the copious details which I have collected on  
 <pb id="E-8-1859" corres="S-8-1859" n="8"/>
<pb id="S-9-1859" corres="E-9-1859" n="9"/><note type="pg"> 9</note><note type="rh">  CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note>this curious subject; but to show how singular the laws are which determine the reproduction of animals under confinement, I may just mention that carnivorous animals, even from the tropics, breed in this country pretty freely under confinement, with the exception of the plantigrades or bear family; whereas, carnivorous birds, with the rarest exceptions, hardly ever lay fertile eggs. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-200-1000-1859">Many exotic plants have pollen utterly worthless, in the same exact condition as in the most sterile hybrids. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-200-1100-1859">When, on the one hand, we see domesticated animals and plants, though often weak and sickly, yet breeding quite freely under confinement; and when, on the other hand, we see individuals, though taken young from a state of nature, perfectly tamed, long-lived, and healthy (of which I could give numerous instances), yet having their reproductive system so seriously affected by unperceived causes as to fail in acting, we need not be surprised at this system, when it does act under confinement, acting not quite regularly, and producing offspring not perfectly like their parents or variable. </ab></p>
<p  n="300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-300-100-1859">Sterility has been said to be the bane of horticulture; but on this view we owe variability to the same cause which produces sterility; and variability is the source of all the choicest productions of the garden. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-300-200-1859">I may add, that as some organisms will breed most freely under the most unnatural conditions (for instance, the rabbit and ferret kept in hutches), showing that their reproductive system has not been thus affected; so will some animals and plants withstand domestication or cultivation, and vary very slightly--perhaps hardly more than in a state of nature. </ab></p>
<p  n="400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-400-100-1859">A long list could easily be given of "sporting plants;" by this term gardeners mean a single bud or offset, which suddenly assumes a new and sometimes very different character from that of the rest of the plant. <note type="rh"> B 3</note> 
 <pb id="E-9-1859" corres="S-9-1859" n="9"/>
<pb id="S-10-1859" corres="E-10-1859" n="10"/><note type="pg"> 10</note> <note type="rh">  VARIATION CHAP. I.</note></ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-400-200-1859">Such buds can be propagated by grafting, etc., and sometimes by seed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-400-300-1859">These "sports" are extremely rare under nature, but far from rare under cultivation; and in this case we see that the treatment of the parent has affected a bud or offset, and not the ovules or pollen. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-400-400-1859">But it is the opinion of most physiologists that there is no essential difference between a bud and an ovule in their earliest stages of formation; so that, in fact, "sports" support my view, that variability may be largely attributed to the ovules or pollen, or to both, having been affected by the treatment of the parent prior to the act of conception. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-400-500-1859">These cases anyhow show that variation is not necessarily connected, as some authors have supposed, with the act of generation. </ab></p>
<p  n="500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-500-100-1859">Seedlings from the same fruit, and the young of the same litter, sometimes differ considerably from each other, though both the young and the parents, as Müller has remarked, have apparently been exposed to exactly the same conditions of life; and this shows how unimportant the direct effects of the conditions of life are in comparison with the laws of reproduction, and of growth, and of inheritance; for had the action of the conditions been direct, if any of the young had varied, all would probably have varied in the same manner. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-500-200-1859">To judge how much, in the case of any variation, we should attribute to the direct action of heat, moisture, light, food, etc., is most difficult: my impression is, that with animals such agencies have produced very little direct effect, though apparently more in the case of plants. Under this point of view, Mr. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-500-300-1859">Buckman's recent experiments on plants seem extremely valuable. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-500-400-1859">When all or nearly all the individuals exposed to certain conditions are affected in the same way, the change at first appears to be directly due to such conditions; but in some cases it can be shown that quite opposite conditions produce   
 <pb id="E-10-1859" corres="S-10-1859" n="10"/>
<pb id="S-11-1859" corres="E-11-1859" n="11"/> <note type="pg"> 11</note><note type="rh">  CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note>similar changes of structure. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-500-500-1859">Nevertheless some slight amount of change may, I think, be attributed to the direct action of the conditions of life--as, in some cases, increased size from amount of food, colour from particular kinds of food and from light, and perhaps the thickness of fur from climate. </ab></p>
<p  n="600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-600-100-1859">Habit also has a decided influence, as in the period of flowering with plants when transported from one climate to another. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-600-200-1859">In animals it has a more marked effect; for instance, I find in the domestic duck that the bones of the wing weigh less and the bones of the leg more, in proportion to the whole skeleton, than do the same bones in the wild-duck; and I presume that this change may be safely attributed to the domestic duck flying much less, and walking more, than its wild parent. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-600-300-1859">The great and inherited development of the udders in cows and goats in countries where they are habitually milked, in comparison with the state of these organs in other countries, is another instance of the effect of use. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-600-400-1859">Not a single domestic animal can be named which has not in some country drooping ears; and the view suggested by some authors, that the drooping is due to the disuse of the muscles of the ear, from the animals not being much alarmed by danger, seems probable. </ab></p>
<p  n="700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-700-100-1859">There are many laws regulating variation, some few of which can be dimly seen, and will be hereafter briefly mentioned. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-700-200-1859">I will here only allude to what may be called correlation of growth. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-700-300-1859">Any change in the embryo or larva will almost certainly entail changes in the mature animal. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-700-400-1859">In monstrosities, the correlations between quite distinct parts are very curious; and many instances are given in Isidore Geoffroy St. Hilaire's great work on this subject. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-700-500-1859">Breeders believe that long limbs are almost always accompanied by an elongated head. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-700-600-1859">Some instances of correlation are quite whimsical: thus  
 <pb id="E-11-1859" corres="S-11-1859" n="11"/>
<pb id="S-12-1859" corres="E-12-1859" n="12"/><note type="pg"> 12 </note><note type="rh"> VARIATION.</note> cats with blue eyes are invariably deaf; colour and constitutional peculiarities go together, of which many remarkable cases could be given amongst animals and plants. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-700-700-1859">From the facts collected by Heusinger, it appears that white sheep and pigs are differently affected from coloured individuals by certain vegetable poisons. Hairless dogs have imperfect teeth; long-haired and coarse-haired animals are apt to have, as is asserted, long or many horns; pigeons with feathered feet have skin between their outer toes; pigeons with short beaks have small feet, and those with long beaks large feet. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-700-800-1859">Hence, if man goes on selecting, and thus augmenting, any peculiarity, he will almost certainly unconsciously modify other parts of the structure, owing to the mysterious laws of the correlation of growth. </ab></p>
<p  n="800">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-800-100-1859">The result of the various, quite unknown, or dimly seen laws of variation is infinitely complex and diversified. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-800-200-1859">It is well worth while carefully to study the several treatises published on some of our old cultivated plants, as on the hyacinth, potato, even the dahlia, etc.; and it is really surprising to note the endless points in structure and constitution in which the varieties and sub-varieties differ slightly from each other. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-800-300-1859">The whole organisation seems to have become plastic, and tends to depart in some small degree from that of the parental type. </ab></p>
<p  n="900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-900-100-1859">Any variation which is not inherited is unimportant for us. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-900-200-1859">But the number and diversity of inheritable deviations of structure, both those of slight and those of considerable physiological importance, is endless. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-900-300-1859">Dr.  Prosper Lucas's treatise, in two large volumes, is the fullest and the best on this subject. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-900-400-1859">No breeder doubts how strong is the tendency to inheritance: like produces like is his fundamental belief: doubts have been thrown on this principle by theoretical writers alone. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-900-500-1859">When a  
 <pb id="E-12-1859" corres="S-12-1859" n="12"/>
<pb id="S-13-1859" corres="E-13-1859" n="13"/><note type="pg"> 13</note><note type="rh"> CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note>deviation appears not unfrequently, and we see it in the father and child, we cannot tell whether it may not be due to the same original cause acting on both; but when amongst individuals, apparently exposed to the same conditions, any very rare deviation, due to some extraordinary combination of circumstances, appears in the parent--say, once amongst several million individuals--and it reappears in the child, the mere doctrine of chances almost compels us to attribute its reappearance to inheritance. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-900-600-1859">Every one must have heard of cases of albinism, prickly skin, hairy bodies, etc., appearing in several members of the same family. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-900-700-1859">If strange and rare deviations of structure are truly inherited, less strange and commoner deviations may be freely admitted to be inheritable. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-900-800-1859">Perhaps the correct way of viewing the whole subject, would be, to look at the inheritance of every character whatever as the rule, and non-inheritance as the anomaly. </ab></p>
<p  n="1000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1000-100-1859">The laws governing inheritance are quite unknown; no one can say why the same peculiarity in different individuals of the same species, and in individuals of different species, is sometimes inherited and sometimes not so; why the child often reverts in certain characters to its grandfather or grandmother or other much more remote ancestor; why a peculiarity is often transmitted from one sex to both sexes, or to one sex alone, more commonly but not exclusively to the like sex. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1000-200-1859">It is a fact of some little importance to us, that peculiarities appearing in the males of our domestic breeds are often transmitted either exclusively, or in a much greater degree, to males alone. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1000-300-1859">A much more important rule, which I think may be trusted, is that, at whatever period of life a peculiarity first appears, it tends to appear in the offspring at a corresponding age, though sometimes earlier. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1000-400-1859">In many cases this could  
 <pb id="E-13-1859" corres="S-13-1859" n="13"/>
<pb id="S-14-1859" corres="E-14-1859" n="14"/><note type="pg"> 14</note> <note type="rh">  VARIATION. CHAP. I.</note>not be otherwise: thus the inherited peculiarities in the horns of cattle could appear only in the offspring when nearly mature; peculiarities in the silkworm are known to appear at the corresponding caterpillar or cocoon stage. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1000-500-1859">But hereditary diseases and some other facts make me believe that the rule has a wider extension, and that when there is no apparent reason why a peculiarity should appear at any particular age, yet that it does tend to appear in the offspring at the same period at which it first appeared in the parent. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1000-600-1859">I believe this rule to be of the highest importance in explaining the laws of embryology. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-1000-700-1859">These remarks are of course confined to the first <hi rend="ital">appearance</hi> of the peculiarity, and not to its primary cause, which may have acted on the ovules or male element; in nearly the same manner as in the crossed offspring from a short-horned cow by a long-horned bull, the greater length of horn, though appearing late in life, is clearly due to the male element. </ab></p>
<p  n="1100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1100-100-1859">Having alluded to the subject of reversion, I may here refer to a statement often made by naturalists--namely, that our domestic varieties, when run wild, gradually but certainly revert in character to their aboriginal stocks. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1100-200-1859">Hence it has been argued that no deductions can be drawn from domestic races to species in a state of nature. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1100-300-1859">I have in vain endeavoured to discover on what decisive facts the above statement has so often and so boldly been made. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1100-400-1859">There would be great difficulty in proving its truth: we may safely conclude that very many of the most strongly-marked domestic varieties could not possibly live in a wild state. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1100-500-1859">In many cases we do not know what the aboriginal stock was, and so could not tell whether or not nearly perfect reversion had ensued. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1100-600-1859">It would be quite necessary, in order to prevent the effects of intercrossing, that only a  
 <pb id="E-14-1859" corres="S-14-1859" n="14"/>
<pb id="S-15-1859" corres="E-15-1859" n="15"/><note type="pg"> 15</note><note type="rh">   CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note>single variety should be turned loose in its new home. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-1100-700-1859">Nevertheless, as our varieties certainly do occasionally revert in some of their characters to ancestral forms, it seems to me not improbable, that if we could succeed in naturalising, or were to cultivate, during many generations, the several races, for instance, of the cabbage, in very poor soil (in which case, however, some effect would have to be attributed to the direct action of the poor soil), that they would to a large extent, or even wholly, revert to the wild aboriginal stock. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-1100-800-1859">Whether or not the experiment would succeed, is not of great importance for our line of argument; for by the experiment itself the conditions of life are changed. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-1100-900-1859">If it could be shown that our domestic varieties manifested a strong tendency to reversion,--that is, to lose their acquired characters, whilst kept under unchanged conditions, and whilst kept in a considerable body, so that free intercrossing might check, by blending together, any slight deviations of structure, in such case, I grant that we could deduce nothing from domestic varieties in regard to species. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-1100-1000-1859">But there is not a shadow of evidence in favour of this view: to assert that we could not breed our cart and race-horses, long and short-horned cattle, and poultry of various breeds, and esculent vegetables, for an almost infinite number of generations, would be opposed to all experience. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-1100-1100-1859">I may add, that when under nature the conditions of life do change, variations and reversions of character probably do occur; but natural selection, as will hereafter be explained, will determine how far the new characters thus arising shall be preserved. </ab></p>
<p  n="1200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1200-100-1859">When we look to the hereditary varieties or races of our domestic animals and plants, and compare them with species closely allied together, we generally perceive in each domestic race, as already remarked, less uniformity of character than in true species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1200-200-1859">Domestic races of  
 <pb id="E-15-1859" corres="S-15-1859" n="15"/>
<pb id="S-16-1859" corres="E-16-1859" n="16"/> <note type="pg"> 16</note><note type="rh">   VARIATION. CHAP. I.</note>the same species, also, often have a somewhat monstrous character; by which I mean, that, although differing from each other, and from the other species of the same genus, in several trifling respects, they often differ in an extreme degree in some one part, both when compared one with another, and more especially when compared with all the species in nature to which they are nearest allied. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1200-300-1859">With these exceptions (and with that of the perfect fertility of varieties when crossed,--a subject hereafter to be discussed), domestic races of the same species differ from each other in the same manner as, only in most cases in a lesser degree than, do closely-allied species of the same genus in a state of nature. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1200-400-1859">I think this must be admitted, when we find that there are hardly any domestic races, either amongst animals or plants, which have not been ranked by some competent judges as mere varieties, and by other competent judges as the descendants of aboriginally distinct species. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1200-500-1859">If any marked distinction existed between domestic races and species, this source of doubt could not so perpetually recur. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1200-600-1859">It has often been stated that domestic races do not differ from each other in characters of generic value. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-1200-700-1859">I think it could be shown that this statement is hardly correct; but naturalists differ most widely in determining what characters are of generic value; all such valuations being at present empirical. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-1200-800-1859">Moreover, on the view of the origin of genera which I shall presently give, we have no right to expect often to meet with generic differences in our domesticated productions. </ab></p>
<p  n="1300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1300-100-1859">When we attempt to estimate the amount of structural difference between the domestic races of the same species, we are soon involved in doubt, from not knowing whether they have descended from one or several parent-species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1300-200-1859">This point, if it could be cleared up, would be interesting; if, for instance, it could be shown that the grey-  
 <pb id="E-16-1859" corres="S-16-1859" n="16"/>
<pb id="S-17-1859" corres="E-17-1859" n="17"/><note type="pg"> 17</note><note type="rh">   CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note>hound, bloodhound, terrier, spaniel, and bull-dog, which we all know propagate their kind so truly, were the offspring of any single species, then such facts would have great weight in making us doubt about the immutability of the many very closely allied and natural species--for instance, of the many foxes--inhabiting different quarters of the world. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1300-300-1859">I do not believe, as we shall presently see, that all our dogs have descended from any one wild species; but, in the case of some other domestic races, there is presumptive, or even strong, evidence in favour of this view. </ab></p>
<p  n="1400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1400-100-1859">It has often been assumed that man has chosen for domestication animals and plants having an extraordinary inherent tendency to vary, and likewise to withstand diverse climates. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1400-200-1859">I do not dispute that these capacities have added largely to the value of most of our domesticated productions; but how could a savage possibly know, when he first tamed an animal, whether it would vary in succeeding generations, and whether it would endure other climates? </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1400-300-1859">Has the little variability of the ass or guinea-fowl, or the small power of endurance of warmth by the rein-deer, or of cold by the common camel, prevented their domestication? </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1400-400-1859">I cannot doubt that if other animals and plants, equal in number to our domesticated productions, and belonging to equally diverse classes and countries, were taken from a state of nature, and could be made to breed for an equal number of generations under domestication, they would vary on an average as largely as the parent species of our existing domesticated productions have varied. </ab></p>
<p  n="1500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1500-100-1859">In the case of most of our anciently domesticated animals and plants, I do not think it is possible to come to any definite conclusion, whether they have descended from one or several species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1500-200-1859">The argument mainly relied on by those who believe in the multiple origin  
 <pb id="E-17-1859" corres="S-17-1859" n="17"/>
<pb id="S-18-1859" corres="E-18-1859" n="18"/><note type="pg"> 18</note><note type="rh">  VARIATION. CHAP. I.</note>of our domestic animals is, that we find in the most ancient records, more especially on the monuments of Egypt, much diversity in the breeds; and that some of the breeds closely resemble, perhaps are identical with, those still existing. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1500-300-1859">Even if this latter fact were found more strictly and generally true than seems to me to be the case, what does it show, but that some of our breeds originated there, four or five thousand years ago? </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1500-400-1859">But Mr. Horner's researches have rendered it in some degree probable that man sufficiently civilized to have manufactured pottery existed in the valley of the Nile thirteen or fourteen thousand years ago; and who will pretend to say how long before these ancient periods, savages, like those of Tierra del Fuego or Australia, who possess a semi-domestic dog, may not have existed in Egypt? </ab></p>
<p  n="1600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1600-100-1859">The whole subject must, I think, remain vague; neverthelsss, I may, without here entering on any details, state that, from geographical and other considerations, I think it highly probable that our domestic dogs have descended from several wild species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1600-200-1859">In regard to sheep and goats I can form no opinion. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1600-300-1859">I should think, from facts communicated to me by Mr. Blyth, on the habits, voice, and constitution, etc., of the humped Indian cattle, that these had descended from a different aboriginal stock from our European cattle; and several competent judges believe that these latter have had more than one wild parent. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1600-400-1859">With respect to horses, from reasons which I cannot give here, I am doubtfully inclined to believe, in opposition to several authors, that all the races have descended from one wild stock. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1600-500-1859">Mr. Blyth, whose opinion, from his large and varied stores of knowledge, I should value more than that of almost any one, thinks that all the breeds of poultry have proceeded from the common wild  
 <pb id="E-18-1859" corres="S-18-1859" n="18"/>
<pb id="S-19-1859" corres="E-19-1859" n="19"/><note type="pg"> 19</note> <note type="rh">   CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note>Indian fowl (Gallus bankiva). </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1600-600-1859">In regard to ducks and rabbits, the breeds of which differ considerably from each other in structure, I do not doubt that they all have descended from the common wild duck and rabbit. </ab></p>
<p  n="1700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1700-100-1859">The doctrine of the origin of our several domestic races from several aboriginal stocks, has been carried to an absurd extreme by some authors. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1700-200-1859">They believe that every race which breeds true, let the distinctive characters be ever so slight, has had its wild prototype. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1700-300-1859">At this rate there must have existed at least a score of species of wild cattle, as many sheep, and several goats in Europe alone, and several even within Great Britain. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1700-400-1859">One author believes that there formerly existed in Great Britain eleven wild species of sheep peculiar to it! </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1700-500-1859">When we bear in mind that Britain has now hardly one peculiar mammal, and France but few distinct from those of Germany and conversely, and so with Hungary, Spain, etc., but that each of these kingdoms possesses several peculiar breeds of cattle, sheep, etc., we must admit that many domestic breeds have originated in Europe; for whence could they have been derived, as these several countries do not possess a number of peculiar species as distinct parent-stocks? </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1700-600-1859">So it is in India. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-1700-700-1859">Even in the case of the domestic dogs of the whole world, which I fully admit have probably descended from several wild species, I cannot doubt that there has been an immense amount of inherited variation. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-1700-800-1859">Who can believe that animals closely resembling the Italian greyhound, the bloodhound, the bull-dog, or Blenheim spaniel, etc.--so unlike all wild Canidae--ever existed freely in a state of nature? </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-1700-900-1859">It has often been loosely said that all our races of dogs have been produced by the crossing of a few aboriginal species; but by crossing we can get only forms in some degree intermediate between their parents; and if we  
 <pb id="E-19-1859" corres="S-19-1859" n="19"/>
<pb id="S-20-1859" corres="E-20-1859" n="20"/><note type="pg"> 20</note> <note type="rh">  DOMESTIC PIGEONS. CHAP. I.</note>account for our several domestic races by this process, we must admit the former existence of the most extreme forms, as the Italian greyhound, bloodhound, bull-dog, etc., in the wild state. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-1700-1000-1859">Moreover, the possibility of making distinct races by crossing has been greatly exaggerated. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-1700-1100-1859">There can be no doubt that a race may be modified by occasional crosses, if aided by the careful selection of those individual mongrels, which present any desired character; but that a race could be obtained nearly intermediate between two extremely different races or speceies, I can hardly believe. </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH1-1700-1200-1859">Sir J. Sebright expressly experimentised for this object, and failed. </ab>
<ab  n="1300" id="CH1-1700-1300-1859">The offspring from the first cross between two pure breeds is tolerably and sometimes (as I have found with pigeons) extremely uniform, and everything seems simple enough; but when these mongrels are crossed one with another for several generations, hardly two of them will be alike, and then the extreme difficulty, or rather utter hopelessness, of the task becomes apparent. </ab>
<ab  n="1400" id="CH1-1700-1400-1859">Certainly, a breed intermediate between <hi rend="ital">two very distinct</hi> breeds could not be got without extreme care and long-continued selection; nor can I find a single case on record of a permanent race having been thus formed. </ab></p>
<p  n="1800">
<ab  n="ST" id="CH1-1800-ST-1859"><hi rend="ital">On the Breeds of the Domestic Pigeon</hi> .--Believing that it is always best to study some special group, I have, after deliberation, taken up domestic pigeons. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1800-200-1859">I have kept every breed which I could purchase or obtain, and have been most kindly favoured with skins from several quarters of the world, more especially by the Hon. W. Elliot from India, and by the Hon. C. Murray from Persia. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1800-300-1859">Many treatises in different languages have been published on pigeons, and some of them are very important, as being of considerable antiquity. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1800-400-1859">I have associated with several eminent fanciers, and have been permitted to join two  
 <pb id="E-20-1859" corres="S-20-1859" n="20"/>
<pb id="S-21-1859" corres="E-21-1859" n="21"/><note type="pg">21</note> <note type="rh">  CHAP. I. DOMESTIC PIGEONS.</note>of the London Pigeon Clubs. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1800-500-1859">The diversity of the breeds is something astonishing. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1800-600-1859">Compare the English carrier and the short-faced tumbler, and see the wonderful difference in their beaks, entailing corresponding differences in their skulls. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-1800-700-1859">The carrier, more especially the male bird, is also remarkable from the wonderful development of the carunculated skin about the head, and this is accompanied by greatly elongated eyelids, very large external orifices to the nostrils, and a wide gape of mouth. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-1800-800-1859">The short-faced tumbler has a beak in outline almost like that of a finch; and the common tumbler has the singular and strictly inherited habit of flying at a great height in a compact flock, and tumbling in the air head over heels. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-1800-900-1859">The runt is a bird of great size, with long, massive beak and large feet; some of the sub-breeds of runts have very long necks, others very long wings and tails, others singularly short tails. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-1800-1000-1859">The barb is allied to the carrier, but, instead of a very long beak, has a very short and very broad one. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-1800-1100-1859">The pouter has a much elongated body, wings, and legs; and its enormously developed crop, which it glories in inflating, may well excite astonishment and even laughter. </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH1-1800-1200-1859">The turbit has a very short and conical beak, with a line of reversed feathers down the breast; and it has the habit of continually expanding slightly the upper part of the Oesophagus. </ab>
<ab  n="1300" id="CH1-1800-1300-1859">The Jacobin has the feathers so much reversed along the back of the neck that they form a hood, and it has, proportionally to its size, much elongated wing and tail feathers. </ab>
<ab  n="1400" id="CH1-1800-1400-1859">The trumpeter and laugher, as their names express, utter a very different coo from the other breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="1500" id="CH1-1800-1500-1859">The fantail has thirty or even forty tail-feathers, instead of twelve or fourteen, the normal number in all members of the great pigeon family; and these feathers are kept expanded, and are carried so erect that in good birds the head and tail  
 <pb id="E-21-1859" corres="S-21-1859" n="21"/>
<pb id="S-22-1859" corres="E-22-1859" n="22"/><note type="pg"> 22</note><note type="rh">   DOMESTIC PIGEONS. CHAP. I.</note>touch; the oil-gland is quite aborted. </ab>
<ab  n="1600" id="CH1-1800-1600-1859">Several other less distinct breeds might have been specified. </ab></p>
<p  n="1900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-1900-100-1859">In the skeletons of the several breeds, the development of the bones of the face in length and breadth and curvature differs enormously. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-1900-200-1859">The shape, as well as the breadth and length of the ramus of the lower jaw, varies in a highly remarkable manner. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-1900-300-1859">The number of the caudal and sacral vertebrae vary; as does the number of the ribs, together with their relative breadth and the presence of processes. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-1900-400-1859">The size and shape of the apertures in the sternum are highly variable; so is the degree of divergence and relative size of the two arms of the furcula. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-1900-500-1859">The proportional width of the gape of mouth, the proportional length of the eyelids, of the orifice of the nostrils, of the tongue (not always in strict correlation with the length of beak), the size of the crop and of the upper part of the Oesophagus; the development and abortion of the oil-gland; the number of the primary wing and caudal feathers; the relative length of wing and tail to each other and to the body; the relative length of leg and of the feet; the number of scutellae on the toes, the development of skin between the toes, are all points of structure which are variable. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-1900-600-1859">The period at which the perfect plumage is acquired varies, as does the state of the down with which the nestling birds are clothed when hatched. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-1900-700-1859">The shape and size of the eggs vary. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-1900-800-1859">The manner of flight differs remarkably; as does in some breeds the voice and disposition. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-1900-900-1859">Lastly, in certain breeds, the males and females have come to differ to a slight degree from each other. </ab></p>
<p  n="2000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2000-100-1859">Altogether at least a score of pigeons might be chosen, which if shown to an ornithologist, and he were told that they were wild birds, would certainly, I think, be ranked by him as well-defined species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2000-200-1859">Moreover, I do not believe that any ornithologist would place  
 <pb id="E-22-1859" corres="S-22-1859" n="22"/>
<pb id="S-23-1859" corres="E-23-1859" n="23"/><note type="pg"> 23</note> <note type="rh">  CHAP. I. DOMESTIC PIGEONS.</note>the English carrier, the short-faced tumbler, the runt, the barb, pouter, and fantail in the same genus; more especially as in each of these breeds several truly-inherited sub-breeds, or species as he might have called them, could be shown him. </ab></p>
<p  n="2100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2100-100-1859">Great as the differences are between the breeds of pigeons, I am fully convinced that the common opinion of naturalists is correct, namely, that all have descended from the rock-pigeon (Columba livia), including under this term several geographical races or sub-species, which differ from each other in the most trifling respects. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2100-200-1859">As several of the reasons which have led me to this belief are in some degree applicable in other cases, I will here briefly give them. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2100-300-1859">If the several breeds are not varieties, and have not proceeded from the rock-pigeon, they must have descended from at least seven or eight aboriginal stocks; for it is impossible to make the present domestic breeds by the crossing of any lesser number: how, for instance, could a pouter be produced by crossing two breeds unless one of the parent-stocks possessed the characteristic enormous crop? </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2100-400-1859">The supposed aboriginal stocks must all have been rock-pigeons, that is, not breeding or willingly perching on trees. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2100-500-1859">But besides C. livia, with its geographical sub-species, only two or three other species of rock-pigeons are known; and these have not any of the characters of the domestic breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-2100-600-1859">Hence the supposed aboriginal stocks must either still exist in the countries where they were originally domesticated, and yet be unknown to ornithologists; and this, considering their size, habits, and remarkable characters, seems very improbable; or they must have become extinct in the wild state. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-2100-700-1859">But birds breeding on precipices, and good fliers, are unlikely to be exterminated; and the common rock-pigeon, which has the same habits with the domestic breeds, has not been exterminated  
 <pb id="E-23-1859" corres="S-23-1859" n="23"/>
<pb id="S-24-1859" corres="E-24-1859" n="24"/><note type="pg"> 24 </note><note type="rh">  DOMESTIC PIGEONS. CHAP. I.</note>even on several of the smaller British islets, or on the shores of the Mediterranean. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-2100-800-1859">Hence the supposed extermination of so many species having similar habits with the rock-pigeon seems to me a very rash assumption. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-2100-900-1859">Moreover, the several above-named domesticated breeds have been transported to all parts of the world, and, therefore, some of them must have been carried back again into their native country; but not one has ever become wild or feral, though the dovecot-pigeon, which is the rock-pigeon in a very slightly altered state, has become feral in several places. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-2100-1000-1859">Again, all recent experience shows that it is most difficult to get any wild animal to breed freely under domestication; yet on the hypothesis of the multiple origin of our pigeons, it must be assumed that at least seven or eight species were so thoroughly domesticated in ancient times by half-civilized man, as to be quite prolific under confinement. </ab></p>
<p  n="2200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2200-100-1859">An argument, as it seems to me, of great weight, and applicable in several other cases, is, that the above-specified breeds, though agreeing generally in constitution, habits, voice, colouring, and in most parts of their structure, with the wild rock-pigeon, yet are certainly highly abnormal in other parts of their structure: we may look in vain throughout the whole great family of Columbidae for a beak like that of the English carrier, or that of the short-faced tumbler, or barb; for reversed feathers like those of the jacobin; for a crop like that of the pouter; for tail-feathers like those of the fantail. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2200-200-1859">Hence it must be assumed not only that half-civilized man succeeded in thoroughly domesticating several species, but that he intentionally or by chance picked out extraordinarily abnormal species; and further, that these very species have since all become extinct or unknown. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2200-300-1859">So many strange contingencies seem to me improbable in the highest degree.  
 <pb id="E-24-1859" corres="S-24-1859" n="24"/>
<pb id="S-25-1859" corres="E-25-1859" n="25"/><note type="pg"> 25</note> <note type="rh">  CHAP. I. DOMESTIC PIGEONS.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="2300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2300-100-1859">Some facts in regard to the colouring of pigeons well deserve consideration. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2300-200-1859">The rock-pigeon is of a slaty-blue, and has a white rump (the Indian sub-species, C. intermedia of Strickland, having it bluish); the tail has a terminal dark bar, with the bases of the outer feathers externally edged with white; the wings have two black bars; some semi-domestic breeds and some apparently truly wild breeds have, besides the two black bars, the wings chequered with black. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2300-300-1859">These several marks do not occur together in any other species of the whole family. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2300-400-1859">Now, in every one of the domestic breeds, taking thoroughly well-bred birds, all the above marks, even to the white edging of the outer tail-feathers, sometimes concur perfectly developed. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2300-500-1859">Moreover, when two birds belonging to two distinct breeds are crossed, neither of which is blue or has any of the above-specified marks, the mongrel offspring are very apt suddenly to acquire these characters; for instance, I crossed some uniformly white fantails with some uniformly black barbs, and they produced mottled brown and black birds; these I again crossed together, and one grandchild of the pure white fantail and pure black barb was of as beautiful a blue colour, with the white rump, double black wing-bar, and barred and white-edged tail-feathers, as any wild rock-pigeon! </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-2300-600-1859">We can understand these facts, on the well-known principle of reversion to ancestral characters, if all the domestic breeds have descended from the rock-pigeon. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-2300-700-1859">But if we deny this, we must make one of the two following highly improbable suppositions. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-2300-800-1859">Either, firstly, that all the several imagined aboriginal stocks were coloured and marked like the rock-pigeon, although no other existing species is thus coloured and marked, so that in each separate breed there might be a tendency to revert to the very same colours and markings. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-2300-900-1859">Or, secondly, <note type="sg"> C</note> 
 <pb id="E-25-1859" corres="S-25-1859" n="25"/>
<pb id="S-26-1859" corres="E-26-1859" n="26"/><note type="pg"> 26</note><note type="rh">   DOMESTIC PIGEONS. CHAP. I.</note>that each breed, even the purest, has within a dozen or, at most, within a score of generations, been crossed by the rock-pigeon: I say within a dozen or twenty generations, for we know of no fact countenancing the belief that the child ever reverts to some one ancestor, removed by a greater number of generations. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-2300-1000-1859">In a breed which has been crossed only once with some distinct breed, the tendency to reversion to any character derived from such cross will naturally become less and less, as in each succeeding generation there will be less of the foreign blood; but when there has been no cross with a distinct breed, and there is a tendency in both parents to revert to a character, which has been lost during some former generation, this tendency, for all that we can see to the contrary, may be transmitted undiminished for an indefinite number of generations. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-2300-1100-1859">These two distinct cases are often confounded in treatises on inheritance. </ab></p>
<p  n="2400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2400-100-1859">Lastly, the hybrids or mongrels from between all the domestic breeds of pigeons are perfectly fertile. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2400-200-1859">I can state this from my own observations, purposely made on the most distinct breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2400-300-1859">Now, it is difficult, perhaps impossible, to bring forward one case of the hybrid offspring of two animals <hi rend="ital">clearly distinct</hi>  being themselves perfectly fertile. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2400-400-1859">Some authors believe that long-continued domestication eliminates this strong tendency to sterility: from the history of the dog I think there is some probability in this hypothesis, if applied to species closely related together, though it is unsupported by a single experiment. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2400-500-1859">But to extend the hypothesis so far as to suppose that species, aboriginally as distinct as carriers, tumblers, pouters, and fantails now are, should yield offspring perfectly fertile, <hi rend="ital">inter se</hi> , seems to me rash in the extreme. </ab></p>
<p  n="2500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2500-100-1859">From these several reasons, namely, the improbability of man having formerly got seven or eight supposed  
 <pb id="E-26-1859" corres="S-26-1859" n="26"/>
<pb id="S-27-1859" corres="E-27-1859" n="27"/><note type="pg"> 27</note> <note type="rh"> CHAP. I. DOMESTIC PIGEONS.</note>species of pigeons to breed freely under domestication; these supposed species being quite unknown in a wild state, and their becoming nowhere feral; these species having very abnormal characters in certain respects, as compared with all other Columbidae, though so like in most other respects to the rock-pigeon; the blue colour and various marks occasionally appearing in all the breeds, both when kept pure and when crossed; the mongrel offspring being perfectly fertile;--from these several reasons, taken together, I can feel no doubt that all our domestic breeds have descended from the Columba livia with its geographical sub-species. </ab></p>
<p  n="2600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2600-100-1859">In favour of this view, I may add, firstly, that C. livia, or the rock-pigeon, has been found capable of domestication in Europe and in India; and that it agrees in habits and in a great number of points of structure with all the domestic breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2600-200-1859">Secondly, although an English carrier or short-faced tumbler differs immensely in certain characters from the rock-pigeon, yet by comparing the several sub-breeds of these breeds, more especially those brought from distant countries, we can make an almost perfect series between the extremes of structure. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2600-300-1859">Thirdly, those characters which are mainly distinctive of each breed, for instance the wattle and length of beak of the carrier, the shortness of that of the tumbler, and the number of tail-feathers in the fantail, are in each breed eminently variable; and the explanation of this fact will be obvious when we come to treat of selection. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2600-400-1859">Fourthly, pigeons have been watched, and tended with the utmost care, and loved by many people. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2600-500-1859">They have been domesticated for thousands of years in several quarters of the world; the earliest known record of pigeons is in the fifth Aegyptian dynasty, about 3000 B.C., as was pointed out to me by Professor Lepsius; but Mr. Birch informs me that pigeons are given in a bill <note type="sg"> C2     </note> 
 <pb id="E-27-1859" corres="S-27-1859" n="27"/>
<pb id="S-28-1859" corres="E-28-1859" n="28"/><note type="pg"> 28</note> <note type="rh">  DOMESTIC PIGEONS. CHAP. I.</note>of fare in the previous dynasty. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-2600-600-1859">In the time of the Romans, as we hear from Pliny, immense prices were given for pigeons; "nay, they are come to this pass, that they can reckon up their pedigree and race." Pigeons were much valued by Akber Khan in India, about the year 1600; never less than 20,000 pigeons were taken with the court. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-2600-700-1859">"The monarchs of Iran and Turan sent him some very rare birds;" and, continues the courtly historian, "His Majesty by crossing the breeds, which method was never practised before, has improved them astonishingly." About this same period the Dutch were as eager about pigeons as were the old Romans. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-2600-800-1859">The paramount importance of these considerations in explaining the immense amount of variation which pigeons have undergone, will be obvious when we treat of Selection. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-2600-900-1859">We shall then, also, see how it is that the breeds so often have a somewhat monstrous character. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-2600-1000-1859">It is also a most favourable circumstance for the production of distinct breeds, that male and female pigeons can be easily mated for life; and thus different breeds can be kept together in the same aviary. </ab></p>
<p  n="2700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2700-100-1859">I have discussed the probable origin of domestic pigeons at some, yet quite insufficient, length; because when I first kept pigeons and watched the several kinds, knowing well how true they bred, I felt fully as much difficulty in believing that they could ever have descended from a common parent, as any naturalist could in coming to a similar conclusion in regard to the many species of finches, or other large groups of birds, in nature. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2700-200-1859">One circumstance has struck me much; namely, that all the breeders of the various domestic animals and the cultivators of plants, with whom I have ever conversed, or whose treatises I have read, are firmly convinced that the several breeds to which each has attended, are descended from so many aboriginally distinct species.  
 <pb id="E-28-1859" corres="S-28-1859" n="28"/>
<pb id="S-29-1859" corres="E-29-1859" n="29"/><note type="pg"> 29</note><note type="rh">   CHAP. I. SELECTION BY MAN.</note></ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2700-300-1859">Ask, as I have asked, a celebrated raiser of Hereford cattle, whether his cattle might not have descended from long-horns, and he will laugh you to scorn. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2700-400-1859">I have never met a pigeon, or poultry, or duck, or rabbit fancier, who was not fully convinced that each main breed was descended from a distinct species. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2700-500-1859">Van Mons, in his treatise on pears and apples, shows how utterly he disbelieves that the several sorts, for instance a Ribston-pippin or Codlin-apple, could ever have proceeded from the seeds of the same tree. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-2700-600-1859">Innumerable other examples could be given. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-2700-700-1859">The explanation, I think, is simple: from long-continued study they are strongly impressed with the differences between the several races; and though they well know that each race varies slightly, for they win their prizes by selecting such slight differences, yet they ignore all general arguments, and refuse to sum up in their minds slight differences accumulated during many successive generations. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-2700-800-1859">May not those naturalists who, knowing far less of the laws of inheritance than does the breeder, and knowing no more than he does of the intermediate links in the long lines of descent, yet admit that many of our domestic races have descended from the same parents--may they not learn a lesson of caution, when they deride the idea of species in a state of nature being lineal descendants of other species? </ab></p>
<p  n="2800">
<ab  n="ST" id="CH1-2800-ST-1859"><hi rend="ital">Selection</hi> .-- </ab>
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2800-100-1859">Let us now briefly consider the steps by which domestic races have been produced, either from one or from several allied species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2800-200-1859">Some little effect may, perhaps, be attributed to the direct action of the external conditions of life, and some little to habit; but he would be a bold man who would account by such agencies for the differences of a dray and race horse, a greyhound and bloodhound, a carrier and tumbler pigeon. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2800-300-1859">One of the most remarkable features in our domesticated races  
 <pb id="E-29-1859" corres="S-29-1859" n="29"/>
<pb id="S-30-1859" corres="E-30-1859" n="30"/><note type="rh"> SELECTION BY MAN. CHAP. I.</note><note type="pg"> 30</note>  is that we see in them adaptation, not indeed to the animal's or plant's own good, but to man's use or fancy. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2800-400-1859">Some variations useful to him have probably arisen suddenly, or by one step; many botanists, for instance, believe that the fuller's teazle, with its hooks, which cannot be rivalled by any mechanical contrivance, is only a variety of the wild Dipsacus; and this amount of change may have suddenly arisen in a seedling. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2800-500-1859">So it has probably been with the turnspit dog; and this is known to have been the case with the ancon sheep. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-2800-600-1859">But when we compare the dray-horse and race-horse, the dromedary and camel, the various breeds of sheep fitted either for cultivated land or mountain pasture, with the wool of one breed good for one purpose, and that of another breed for another purpose; when we compare the many breeds of dogs, each good for man in very different ways; when we compare the game-cock, so pertinacious in battle, with other breeds so little quarrelsome, with "everlasting layers" which never desire to sit, and with the bantam so small and elegant; when we compare the host of agricultural, culinary, orchard, and flower-garden races of plants, most useful to man at different seasons and for different purposes, or so beautiful in his eyes, we must, I think, look further than to mere variability. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-2800-700-1859">We cannot suppose that all the breeds were suddenly produced as perfect and as useful as we now see them; indeed, in several cases, we know that this has not been their history. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-2800-800-1859">The key is man's power of accumulative selection: nature gives successive variations; man adds them up in certain directions useful to him. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-2800-900-1859">In this sense he may be said to make for himself useful breeds. </ab></p>
<p  n="2900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-2900-100-1859">The great power of this principle of selection is not hypothetical. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-2900-200-1859">It is certain that several of our eminent breeders have, even within a single lifetime, modified to  
 <pb id="E-30-1859" corres="S-30-1859" n="30"/>
<pb id="S-31-1859" corres="E-31-1859" n="31"/><note type="pg"> 31</note><note type="rh">   CHAP. I. SELECTION BY MAN.</note>a large extent some breeds of cattle and sheep. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-2900-300-1859">In order fully to realise what they have done, it is almost necessary to read several of the many treatises devoted to this subject, and to inspect the animals. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-2900-400-1859">Breeders habitually speak of an animal's organisation as something quite plastic, which they can model almost as they please. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-2900-500-1859">If I had space I could quote numerous passages to this effect from highly competent authorities. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-2900-600-1859">Youatt, who was probably better acquainted with the works of agriculturalists than almost any other individual, and who was himself a very good judge of an animal, speaks of the principle of selection as "that which enables the agriculturist, not only to modify the character of his flock, but to change it altogether. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-2900-700-1859">It is the magician's wand, by means of which he may summon into life whatever form and mould he pleases." </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-2900-800-1859">Lord Somerville, speaking of what breeders have done for sheep, says:--"It would seem as if they had chalked out upon a wall a form perfect in itself, and then had given it existence." </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-2900-900-1859">That most skilful breeder, Sir John Sebright, used to say, with respect to pigeons, that "he would produce any given feather in three years, but it would take him six years to obtain head and beak." </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-2900-1000-1859">In Saxony the importance of the principle of selection in regard to merino sheep is so fully recognised, that men follow it as a trade: the sheep are placed on a table and are studied, like a picture by a connoisseur; this is done three times at intervals of months, and the sheep are each time marked and classed, so that the very best may ultimately be selected for breeding. </ab></p>
<p  n="3000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3000-100-1859">What English breeders have actually effected is proved by the enormous prices given for animals with a good pedigree; and these have now been exported to almost every quarter of the world. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3000-200-1859">The improvement is by no means generally due to crossing different breeds;  
 <pb id="E-31-1859" corres="S-31-1859" n="31"/>
<pb id="S-32-1859" corres="E-32-1859" n="32"/><note type="pg">32 </note><note type="rh">  SELECTION BY MAN. CHAP. I.</note>all the best breeders are strongly opposed to this practice, except sometimes amongst closely allied sub-breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3000-300-1859">And when a cross has been made, the closest selection is far more indispensable even than in ordinary cases. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-3000-400-1859">If selection consisted merely in separating some very distinct variety, and breeding from it, the principle would be so obvious as hardly to be worth notice; but its importance consists in the great effect produced by the accumulation in one direction, during successive generations, of differences absolutely inappreciable by an uneducated eye--differences which I for one have vainly attempted to appreciate. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-3000-500-1859">Not one man in a thousand has accuracy of eye and judgment sufficient to become an eminent breeder. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-3000-600-1859">If gifted with these qualities, and he studies his subject for years, and devotes his lifetime to it with indomitable perseverance, he will succeed, and may make great improvements; if he wants any of these qualities, he will assuredly fail. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-3000-700-1859">Few would readily believe in the natural capacity and years of practice requisite to become even a skilful pigeon-fancier. </ab></p>
<p  n="3100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3100-100-1859">The same principles are followed by horticulturists; but the variations are here often more abrupt. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3100-200-1859">No one supposes that our choicest productions have been produced by a single variation from the aboriginal stock. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3100-300-1859">We have proofs that this is not so in some cases, in which exact records have been kept; thus, to give a very trifling instance, the steadily-increasing size of the common gooseberry may be quoted. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-3100-400-1859">We see an astonishing improvement in many florists' flowers, when the flowers of the present day are compared with drawings made only twenty or thirty years ago. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-3100-500-1859">When a race of plants is once pretty well established, the seed-raisers do not pick out the best plants, but merely go over their seed-beds, and pull up the "rogues," as they call the plants that deviate from the proper standard. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-3100-600-1859">With animals this  
 <pb id="E-32-1859" corres="S-32-1859" n="32"/>
<pb id="S-33-1859" corres="E-33-1859" n="33"/><note type="pg"> 33</note> <note type="rh">  CHAP. I. METHODICAL SELECTION.</note>kind of selection is, in fact, also followed; for hardly any one is so careless as to allow his worst animals to breed. </ab></p>
<p  n="3200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3200-100-1859">In regard to plants, there is another means of observing the accumulated effects of selection--namely, by comparing the diversity of flowers in the different varieties of the same species in the flower-garden; the diversity of leaves, pods, or tubers, or whatever part is valued, in the kitchen-garden, in comparison with the flowers of the same varieties; and the diversity of fruit of the same species in the orchard, in comparison with the leaves and flowers of the same set of varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3200-200-1859">See how different the leaves of the cabbage are, and how extremely alike the flowers; how unlike the flowers of the heartsease are, and how alike the leaves; how much the fruit of the different kinds of gooseberries differ in size, colour, shape, and hairiness, and yet the flowers present very slight differences. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3200-300-1859">It is not that the varieties which differ largely in some one point do not differ at all in other points; this is hardly ever, perhaps never, the case. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-3200-400-1859">The laws of correlation of growth, the importance of which should never be overlooked, will ensure some differences; but, as a general rule, I cannot doubt that the continued selection of slight variations, either in the leaves, the flowers, or the fruit, will produce races differing from each other chiefly in these characters. </ab></p>
<p  n="3300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3300-100-1859">It may be objected that the principle of selection has been reduced to methodical practice for scarcely more than three-quarters of a century; it has certainly been more attended to of late years, and many treatises have been published on the subject; and the result, I may add, has been, in a corresponding degree, rapid and important. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3300-200-1859">But it is very far from true that the principle is a modern discovery. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3300-300-1859">I could give several references to the full acknowledgment of the importance of the principle in works of high antiquity. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-3300-400-1859">In rude and <note type="sg"> C 3  </note> 
 <pb id="E-33-1859" corres="S-33-1859" n="33"/>
<pb id="S-34-1859" corres="E-34-1859" n="34"/><note type="pg"> 34</note> <note type="rh">  METHODICAL SELECTION. CHAP. I.</note>barbarous periods of English history choice animals were often imported, and laws were passed to prevent their exportation: the destruction of horses under a certain size was ordered, and this may be compared to the "roguing" of plants by nurserymen. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-3300-500-1859">The principle of selection I find distinctly given in an ancient Chinese encyclopaedia. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-3300-600-1859">Explicit rules are laid down by some of the Roman classical writers. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-3300-700-1859">From passages in Genesis, it is clear that the colour of domestic animals was at that early period attended to. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-3300-800-1859">Savages now sometimes cross their dogs with wild canine animals, to improve the breed, and they formerly did so, as is attested by passages in Pliny. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-3300-900-1859">The savages in South Africa match their draught cattle by colour, as do some of the Esquimaux their teams of dogs. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-3300-1000-1859">Livingstone shows how much good domestic breeds are valued by the negroes of the interior of Africa who have not associated with Europeans. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-3300-1100-1859">Some of these facts do not show actual selection, but they show that the breeding of domestic animals was carefully attended to in ancient times, and is now attended to by the lowest savages. </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH1-3300-1200-1859">It would, indeed, have been a strange fact, had attention not been paid to breeding, for the inheritance of good and bad qualities is so obvious. </ab></p>
<p  n="3400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3400-100-1859">At the present time, eminent breeders try by methodical selection, with a distinct object in view, to make a new strain or sub-breed, superior to anything existing in the country. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3400-200-1859">But, for our purpose, a kind of Selection, which may be called Unconscious, and which results from every one trying to possess and breed from the best individual animals, is more important. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3400-300-1859">Thus, a man who intends keeping pointers naturally tries to get as good dogs as he can, and afterwards breeds from his own best dogs, but he has no wish or expectation of permanently altering the breed. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-3400-400-1859">Nevertheless I cannot  
 <pb id="E-34-1859" corres="S-34-1859" n="34"/>
<pb id="S-35-1859" corres="E-35-1859" n="35"/><note type="pg"> 35</note> <note type="rh">  CHAP. I. UNCONSCIOUS SELECTION.</note>doubt that this process, continued during centuries, would improve and modify any breed, in the same way as Bakewell, Collins, etc., by this very same process, only carried on more methodically, did greatly modify, even during their own lifetimes, the forms and qualities of their cattle. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-3400-500-1859">Slow and insensible changes of this kind could never be recognised unless actual measurements or careful drawings of the breeds in question had been made long ago, which might serve for comparison. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-3400-600-1859">In some cases, however, unchanged or but little changed individuals of the same breed may be found in less civilised districts, where the breed has been less improved. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-3400-700-1859">There is reason to believe that King Charles's spaniel has been unconsciously modified to a large extent since the time of that monarch. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-3400-800-1859">Some highly competent authorities are convinced that the setter is directly derived from the spaniel, and has probably been slowly altered from it. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-3400-900-1859">It is known that the English pointer has been greatly changed within the last century, and in this case the change has, it is believed, been chiefly effected by crosses with the fox-hound; but what concerns us is, that the change has been effected unconsciously and gradually, and yet so effectually, that, though the old Spanish pointer certainly came from Spain, Mr. Borrow has not seen, as I am informed by him, any native dog in Spain like our pointer. </ab></p>
<p  n="3500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3500-100-1859">By a similar process of selection, and by careful training, the whole body of English racehorses have come to surpass in fleetness and size the parent Arab stock, so that the latter, by the regulations for the Goodwood Races, are favoured in the weights they carry. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3500-200-1859">Lord Spencer and others have shown how the cattle of England have increased in weight and in early maturity, compared with the stock formerly kept in this country. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3500-300-1859">By comparing the accounts given in old pigeon treatises of carriers  
 <pb id="E-35-1859" corres="S-35-1859" n="35"/>
<pb id="S-36-1859" corres="E-36-1859" n="36"/><note type="pg"> 36</note> <note type="rh">  UNCONSCIOUS SELECTION. CHAP. I.</note>and tumblers with these breeds as now existing in Britain, India, and Persia, we can, I think, clearly trace the stages through which they have insensibly passed, and come to differ so greatly from the rock-pigeon. </ab></p>
<p  n="3600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3600-100-1859">Youatt gives an excellent illustration of the effects of a course of selection, which may be considered as unconsciously followed, in so far that the breeders could never have expected or even have wished to have produced the result which ensued--namely, the production of two distinct strains. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3600-200-1859">The two flocks of Leicester sheep kept by Mr. Buckley and Mr. Burgess, as Mr. Youatt remarks, "have been purely bred from the original stock of Mr. Bakewell for upwards of fifty years. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3600-300-1859">There is not a suspicion existing in the mind of any one at all acquainted with the subject that the owner of either of them has deviated in any one instance from the pure blood of Mr. Bakewell's flock, and yet the difference between the sheep possessed by these two gentlemen is so great that they have the appearance of being quite different varieties." </ab></p>
<p  n="3700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3700-100-1859">If there exist savages so barbarous as never to think of the inherited character of the offspring of their domestic animals, yet any one animal particularly useful to them, for any special purpose, would be carefully preserved during famines and other accidents, to which savages are so liable, and such choice animals would thus generally leave more offspring than the inferior ones; so that in this case there would be a kind of unconscious selection going on. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3700-200-1859">We see the value set on animals even by the barbarians of Tierra del Fuego, by their killing and devouring their old women, in times of dearth, as of less value than their dogs. </ab></p>
<p  n="3800">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3800-100-1859">In plants the same gradual process of improvement, through the occasional preservation of the best individuals, whether or not sufficiently distinct to be ranked  
 <pb id="E-36-1859" corres="S-36-1859" n="36"/>
<pb id="S-37-1859" corres="E-37-1859" n="37"/><note type="pg"> 37</note> <note type="rh">   CHAP. I. UNCONSCIOUS SELECTION.</note>at their first appearance as distinct varieties, and whether or not two or more species or races have become blended together by crossing, may plainly be recognised in the increased size and beauty which we now see in the varieties of the heartsease, rose, pelargonium, dahlia, and other plants, when compared with the older varieties or with their parent-stocks. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3800-200-1859">No one would ever expect to get a first-rate heartsease or dahlia from the seed of a wild plant. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3800-300-1859">No one would expect to raise a first-rate melting pear from the seed of the wild pear, though he might succeed from a poor seedling growing wild, if it had come from a garden-stock. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-3800-400-1859">The pear, though cultivated in classical times, appears, from Pliny's description, to have been a fruit of very inferior quality. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-3800-500-1859">I have seen great surprise expressed in horticultural works at the wonderful skill of gardeners, in having produced such splendid results from such poor materials; but the art, I cannot doubt, has been simple, and, as far as the final result is concerned, has been followed almost unconsciously. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-3800-600-1859">It has consisted in always cultivating the best known variety, sowing its seeds, and, when a slightly better variety has chanced to appear, selecting it, and so onwards. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-3800-700-1859">But the gardeners of the classical period, who cultivated the best pear they could procure, never thought what splendid fruit we should eat; though we owe our excellent fruit, in some small degree, to their having naturally chosen and preserved the best varieties they could anywhere find. </ab></p>
<p  n="3900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-3900-100-1859">A large amount of change in our cultivated plants, thus slowly and unconsciously accumulated, explains, as I believe, the well-known fact, that in a vast number of cases we cannot recognise, and therefore do not know, the wild parent-stocks of the plants which have been longest cultivated in our flower and kitchen gardens. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-3900-200-1859">If it has taken centuries or thousands of years to improve  
 <pb id="E-37-1859" corres="S-37-1859" n="37"/>
<pb id="S-38-1859" corres="E-38-1859" n="38"/><note type="pg"> 38</note> <note type="rh">  SELECTION BY MAN. CHAP. I.</note>or modify most of our plants up to their present standard of usefulness to man, we can understand how it is that neither Australia, the Cape of Good Hope, nor any other region inhabited by quite uncivilised man, has afforded us a single plant worth culture. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-3900-300-1859">It is not that these countries, so rich in species, do not by a strange chance possess the aboriginal stocks of any useful plants, but that the native plants have not been improved by continued selection up to a standard of perfection comparable with that given to the plants in countries anciently civilised. </ab></p>
<p  n="4000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4000-100-1859">In regard to the domestic animals kept by uncivilised man, it should not be overlooked that they almost always have to struggle for their own food, at least during certain seasons. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4000-200-1859">And in two countries very differently circumstanced, individuals of the same species, having slightly different constitutions or structure, would often succeed better in the one country than in the other, and thus by a process of "natural selection," as will hereafter be more fully explained, two sub-breeds might be formed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4000-300-1859">This, perhaps, partly explains what has been remarked by some authors, namely, that the varieties kept by savages have more of the character of species than the varieties kept in civilised countries. </ab></p>
<p  n="4100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4100-100-1859">On the view here given of the all-important part which selection by man has played, it becomes at once obvious, how it is that our domestic races show adaptation in their structure or in their habits to man's wants or fancies. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4100-200-1859">We can, I think, further understand the frequently abnormal character of our domestic races, and likewise their differences being so great in external characters and relatively so slight in internal parts or organs. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4100-300-1859">Man can hardly select, or only with much difficulty, any deviation of structure excepting such as is externally visible; and indeed he rarely cares for what is internal. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-4100-400-1859">He can never act by selection, excepting on variations <note type="sg"> 39</note><note type="rh">   CHAP. I. SELECTION BY MAN.</note>which are first given to him in some slight degree by nature. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-4100-500-1859">No man would ever try to make a fantail, till he saw a pigeon with a tail developed in some slight degree in an unusual manner, or a pouter till he saw a pigeon with a crop of somewhat unusual size; and the more abnormal or unusual any character was when it first appeared, the more likely it would be to catch his attention. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-4100-600-1859">But to use such an expression as trying to make a fantail, is, I have no doubt, in most cases, utterly incorrect. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-4100-700-1859">The man who first selected a pigeon with a slightly larger tail, never dreamed what the descendants of that pigeon would become through long-continued, partly unconscious and partly methodical selection. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-4100-800-1859">Perhaps the parent bird of all fantails had only fourteen tail-feathers somewhat expanded, like the present Java fantail, or like individuals of other and distinct breeds, in which as many as seventeen tail-feathers have been counted. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-4100-900-1859">Perhaps the first pouter-pigeon did not inflate its crop much more than the turbit now does the upper part of its Oesophagus,--a habit which is disregarded by all fanciers, as it is not one of the points of the breed. </ab></p>
<p  n="4200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4200-100-1859">Nor let it be thought that some great deviation of structure would be necessary to catch the fancier's eye: he perceives extremely small differences, and it is in human nature to value any novelty, however slight, in one's own possession. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4200-200-1859">Nor must the value which would formerly be set on any slight differences in the individuals of the same species, be judged of by the value which would now be set on them, after several breeds have once fairly been established. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4200-300-1859">Many slight differences might, and indeed do now, arise amongst pigeons, which are rejected as faults or deviations from the standard of perfection of each breed. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-4200-400-1859">The common goose has not given rise to any marked varieties; hence the Thoulouse and the common breed, which differ only in colour, that  
 <pb id="E-38-1859" corres="S-38-1859" n="38"/>
<pb id="S-40-1859" corres="E-40-1859" n="40"/><note type="pg"> 40 </note><note type="rh">  SELECTION BY MAN. CHAP. I.</note>most fleeting of characters, have lately been exhibited as distinct at our poultry-shows. </ab></p>
<p  n="4300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4300-100-1859">I think these views further explain what has sometimes been noticed--namely that we know nothing about the origin or history of any of our domestic breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4300-200-1859">But, in fact, a breed, like a dialect of a language, can hardly be said to have had a definite origin. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4300-300-1859">A man preserves and breeds from an individual with some slight deviation of structure, or takes more care than usual in matching his best animals and thus improves them, and the improved individuals slowly spread in the immediate neighbourhood. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-4300-400-1859">But as yet they will hardly have a distinct name, and from being only slightly valued, their history will be disregarded. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-4300-500-1859">When further improved by the same slow and gradual process, they will spread more widely, and will get recognised as something distinct and valuable, and will then probably first receive a provincial name. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-4300-600-1859">In semi-civilised countries, with little free communication, the spreading and knowledge of any new sub-breed will be a slow process. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-4300-700-1859">As soon as the points of value of the new sub-breed are once fully acknowledged, the principle, as I have called it, of unconscious selection will always tend,--perhaps more at one period than at another, as the breed rises or falls in fashion,--perhaps more in one district than in another, according to the state of civilisation of the inhabitants,--slowly to add to the characteristic features of the breed, whatever they may be. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-4300-800-1859">But the chance will be infinitely small of any record having been preserved of such slow, varying, and insensible changes. </ab></p>
<p  n="4400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4400-100-1859">I must now say a few words on the circumstances, favourable, or the reverse, to man's power of selection. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4400-200-1859">A high degree of variability is obviously favourable, as freely giving the materials for selection to work on; not that mere individual differences are not amply  
 <pb id="E-40-1859" corres="S-40-1859" n="40"/>
<pb id="S-41-1859" corres="E-41-1859" n="41"/><note type="pg"> 41</note> <note type="rh">   CHAP. I. CIRCUMSTANCES FAVOURABLE TO
SELECTION.</note>sufficient, with extreme care, to allow of the accumulation of a large amount of modification in almost any desired direction. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4400-300-1859">But as variations manifestly useful or pleasing to man appear only occasionally, the chance of their appearance will be much increased by a large number of individuals being kept; and hence this comes to be of the highest importance to success. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-4400-400-1859">On this principle Marshall has remarked, with respect to the sheep of parts of Yorkshire, that "as they generally belong to poor people, and are mostly <hi rend="ital">in</hi>  <hi rend="ital">smalllots</hi> , they never can be improved." </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-4400-500-1859">On the other hand, nurserymen, from raising large stocks of the same plants, are generally far more successful than amateurs in getting new and valuable varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-4400-600-1859">The keeping of a large number of individuals of a species in any country requires that the species should be placed under favourable conditions of life, so as to breed freely in that country. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-4400-700-1859">When the individuals of any species are scanty, all the individuals, whatever their quality may be, will generally be allowed to breed, and this will effectually prevent selection. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-4400-800-1859">But probably the most important point of all, is, that the animal or plant should be so highly useful to man, or so much valued by him, that the closest attention should be paid to even the slightest deviation in the qualities or structure of each individual. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-4400-900-1859">Unless such attention be paid nothing can be effected. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-4400-1000-1859">I have seen it gravely remarked, that it was most fortunate that the strawberry began to vary just when gardeners began to attend closely to this plant. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-4400-1100-1859">No doubt the strawberry had always varied since it was cultivated, but the slight varieties had been neglected. </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH1-4400-1200-1859">As soon, however, as gardeners picked out individual plants with slightly larger, earlier, or better fruit, and raised seedlings from them, and again picked out the best seedlings and bred from them, then, there appeared (aided by some  
 <pb id="E-41-1859" corres="S-41-1859" n="41"/>
<pb id="S-42-1859" corres="E-42-1859" n="42"/><note type="pg"> 42</note><note type="rh">   SUMMARY ON VARIATION. CHAP. I.</note>crossing with distinct species) those many admirable varieties of the strawberry which have been raised during the last thirty or forty years. </ab></p>
<p  n="4500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4500-100-1859">In the case of animals with separate sexes, facility in preventing crosses is an important element of success in the formation of new races,--at least, in a country which is already stocked with other races. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4500-200-1859">In this respect enclosure of the land plays a part. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4500-300-1859">Wandering savages or the inhabitants of open plains rarely possess more than one breed of the same species. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-4500-400-1859">Pigeons can be mated for life, and this is a great convenience to the fancier, for thus many races may be kept true, though mingled in the same aviary; and this circumstance must have largely favoured the improvement and formation of new breeds. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-4500-500-1859">Pigeons, I may add, can be propagated in great numbers and at a very quick rate, and inferior birds may be freely rejected, as when killed they serve for food. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-4500-600-1859">On the other hand, cats, from their nocturnal rambling habits, cannot be matched, and, although so much valued by women and children, we hardly ever see a distinct breed kept up; such breeds as we do sometimes see are almost always imported from some other country, often from islands. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-4500-700-1859">Although I do not doubt that some domestic animals vary less than others, yet the rarity or absence of distinct breeds of the cat, the donkey, peacock, goose, etc., may be attributed in main part to selection not having been brought into play: in cats, from the difficulty in pairing them; in donkeys, from only a few being kept by poor people, and little attention paid to their breeding; in peacocks, from not being very easily reared and a large stock not kept; in geese, from being valuable only for two purposes, food and feathers, and more especially from no pleasure having been felt in the display of distinct breeds.  
 <pb id="E-42-1859" corres="S-42-1859" n="42"/>
<pb id="S-43-1859" corres="E-43-1859" n="43"/><note type="pg"> 43</note> <note type="rh">  CHAP. I. UNDER DOMESTICATION.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="4600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH1-4600-100-1859">To sum up on the origin of our Domestic Races of animals and plants. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH1-4600-200-1859">I believe that the conditions of life, from their action on the reproductive system, are so far of the highest importance as causing variability. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH1-4600-300-1859">I do not believe that variability is an inherent and necessary contingency, under all circumstances, with all organic beings, as some authors have thought. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH1-4600-400-1859">The effects of variability are modified by various degrees of inheritance and of reversion. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH1-4600-500-1859">Variability is governed by many unknown laws, more especially by that of correlation of growth. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH1-4600-600-1859">Something may be attributed to the direct action of the conditions of life. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH1-4600-700-1859">Something must be attributed to use and disuse. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH1-4600-800-1859">The final result is thus rendered infinitely complex. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH1-4600-900-1859">In some cases, I do not doubt that the intercrossing of species, aboriginally distinct, has played an important part in the origin of our domestic productions. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH1-4600-1000-1859">When in any country several domestic breeds have once been established, their occasional intercrossing, with the aid of selection, has, no doubt, largely aided in the formation of new sub-breeds; but the importance of the crossing of varieties has, I believe, been greatly exaggerated, both in regard to animals and to those plants which are propagated by seed. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH1-4600-1100-1859">In plants which are temporarily propagated by cuttings, buds, etc., the importance of the crossing both of distinct species and of varieties is immense; for the cultivator here quite disregards the extreme variability both of hybrids and mongrels, and the frequent sterility of hybrids; but the cases of plants not propagated by seed are of little importance to us, for their endurance is only temporary. </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH1-4600-1200-1859">Over all these causes of Change I am convinced that the accumulative action of Selection, whether applied methodically and more quickly, or unconsciously and more slowly, but more efficiently, is by far the predominant Power. </ab></p>
</div>
<pb id="E-43-1859" corres="S-43-1859" n="43"/>
 
 
<pb id="S-44-1859" corres="E-44-1859" n="44"/> <note type="pg"> 44 VARIATION UNDER NATURE. CHAP. II.</note>
<div type="chapter"  n="CH2" >
<ab  n="T" id="CH2-T-1859">CHAPTER II. </ab>
<ab  n="ST" id="CH2-ST-1859">VARIATION UNDER NATURE. </ab>
<ab  n="SQ" id="CH2-SQ-1859">Variability -- Individual differences -- Doubtful species -- Wide ranging, much diffused, and common species vary most -- Species of the larger genera in any country vary more than the species of the smaller genera -- Many of the species of the larger genera resemble varieties in being very closely, but unequally, related to each other, and in having restricted ranges. </ab>
<p  n="100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-100-100-1859">BEFORE applying the principles arrived at in the last chapter to organic beings in a state of nature, we must briefly discuss whether these latter are subject to any variation. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-100-200-1859">To treat this subject at all properly, a long catalogue of dry facts should be given; but these I shall reserve for my future work. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-100-300-1859">Nor shall I here discuss the various definitions which have been given of the term species. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-100-400-1859">No one definition has as yet satisfied all naturalists; yet every naturalist knows vaguely what he means when he speaks of a species. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-100-500-1859">Generally the term includes the unknown element of a distinct act of creation. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-100-600-1859">The term "variety" is almost equally difficult to define; but here community of descent is almost universally implied, though it can rarely be proved. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH2-100-700-1859">We have also what are called monstrosities; but they graduate into varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH2-100-800-1859">By a monstrosity I presume is meant some considerable deviation of structure in one part, either injurious to or not useful to the species, and not generally propagated. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH2-100-900-1859">Some authors use the term "variation" in a technical sense, as implying a modification directly due to the physical conditions of life; and "variations" in this sense are supposed not to be inherited: but who can say that the dwarfed condition of shells in the brackish waters of the Baltic, or dwarfed  
 <pb id="E-44-1859" corres="S-44-1859" n="44"/>
<pb id="S-45-1859" corres="E-45-1859" n="45"/> <note type="pg"> 45 CHAP. II. VARIATION UNDER NATURE.</note>plants on Alpine summits, or the thicker fur of an animal from far northwards, would not in some cases be inherited for at least some few generations? </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH2-100-1000-1859">and in this case I presume that the form would be called a variety. </ab></p>
<p  n="200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-200-100-1859">Again, we have many slight differences which may be called individual differences, such as are known frequently to appear in the offspring from the same parents, or which may be presumed to have thus arisen, from being frequently observed in the individuals of the same species inhabiting the same confined locality. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-200-200-1859">No one supposes that all the individuals of the same species are cast in the very same mould.  </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-200-300-1859">These individual differences are highly important for us, as they afford materials for natural selection to accumulate, in the same manner as man can accumulate in any given direction individual differences in his domesticated productions. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-200-400-1859">These individual differences generally affect what naturalists consider unimportant parts; but I could show by a long catalogue of facts, that parts which must be called important, whether viewed under a physiological or classificatory point of view, sometimes vary in the individuals of the same species. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-200-500-1859">I am convinced that the most experienced naturalist would be surprised at the number of the cases of variability, even in important parts of structure, which he could collect on good authority, as I have collected, during a course of years. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-200-600-1859">It should be remembered that systematists are far from pleased at finding variability in important characters, and that there are not many men who will laboriously examine internal and important organs, and compare them in many specimens of the same species. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH2-200-700-1859">I should never have expected that the branching of the main nerves close to the great central ganglion of an insect would have been variable in the same species; I should have expected that changes of this nature could have been effected only  
 <pb id="E-45-1859" corres="S-45-1859" n="45"/>
<pb id="S-46-1859" corres="E-46-1859" n="46"/> <note type="pg"> 46 VARIATION UNDER NATURE. CHAP. II.</note>by slow degrees: yet quite recently Mr. Lubbock has shown a degree of variability in these main nerves in Coccus, which may almost be compared to the irregular branching of the stem of a tree. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH2-200-800-1859">This philosophical naturalist, I may add, has also quite recently shown that the muscles in the larvae of certain insects are very far from uniform.  </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH2-200-900-1859">Authors sometimes argue in a circle when they state that important organs never vary; for these same authors practically rank that character as important (as some few naturalists have honestly confessed) which does not vary; and, under this point of view, no instance of an important part varying will ever be found: but under any other point of view many instances assuredly can be given. </ab></p>
<p  n="300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-300-100-1859">There is one point connected with individual differences, which seems to me extremely perplexing: I refer to those genera which have sometimes been called "protean" or "polymorphic," in which the species present an inordinate amount of variation; and hardly two naturalists can agree which forms to rank as species and which as varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-300-200-1859">We may instance Rubus, Rosa, and Hieracium amongst plants, several genera of insects, and several genera of Brachiopod shells. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-300-300-1859">In most polymorphic genera some of the species have fixed and definite characters. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-300-400-1859">Genera which are polymorphic in one country seem to be, with some few exceptions, polymorphic in other countries, and likewise, judging from Brachiopod shells, at former periods of time. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-300-500-1859">These facts seem to be very perplexing, for they seem to show that this kind of variability is independent of the conditions of life. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-300-600-1859">I am inclined to suspect that we see in these polymorphic genera variations in points of structure which are of no service or disservice to the species, and which consequently have not been seized on and rendered definite by natural selection, as hereafter will be explained.  
 <pb id="E-46-1859" corres="S-46-1859" n="46"/>
<pb id="S-47-1859" corres="E-47-1859" n="47"/> <note type="pg"> 47 CHAP. II. DOUBTFUL SPECIES.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-400-100-1859">Those forms which possess in some considerable degree the character of species, but which are so closely similar to some other forms, or are so closely linked to them by intermediate gradations, that naturalists do not like to rank them as distinct species, are in several respects the most important for us. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-400-200-1859">We have every reason to believe that many of these doubtful and closely-allied forms have permanently retained their characters in their own country for a long time; for as long, as far as we know, as have good and true species.  </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-400-300-1859">Practically, when a naturalist can unite two forms together by others having intermediate characters, he treats the one as a variety of the other, ranking the most common, but sometimes the one first described, as the species, and the other as the variety. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-400-400-1859">But cases of great difficulty, which I will not here enumerate, sometimes occur in deciding whether or not to rank one form as a variety of another, even when they are closely connected by intermediate links; nor will the commonly-assumed hybrid nature of the intermediate links always remove the difficulty. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-400-500-1859">In very many cases, however, one form is ranked as a variety of another, not because the intermediate links have actually been found, but because analogy leads the observer to suppose either that they do now somewhere exist, or may formerly have existed; and here a wide door for the entry of doubt and conjecture is opened. </ab></p>
<p  n="500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-500-100-1859">Hence, in determining whether a form should be ranked as a species or a variety, the opinion of naturalists having sound judgment and wide experience seems the only guide to folloW. We must, however, in many cases, decide by a majority of naturalists, for few well-marked and well-known varieties can be named which have not been ranked as species by at least some competent judges.  
 <pb id="E-47-1859" corres="S-47-1859" n="47"/>
<pb id="S-48-1859" corres="E-48-1859" n="48"/> <note type="pg"> 48 DOUBTFUL SPECIES. CHAP. II.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-600-100-1859">That varieties of this doubtful nature are far from uncommon cannot be disputed. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-600-200-1859">Compare the several floras of Great Britain, of France or of the United States, drawn up by different botanists, and see what a surprising number of forms have been ranked by one botanist as good species, and by another as mere varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-600-300-1859">Mr. H. C. Watson, to whom I lie under deep obligation for assistance of all kinds, has marked for me 182 British plants, which are generally considered as varieties, but which have all been ranked by botanists as species; and in making this list he has omitted many trifling varieties, but which nevertheless have been ranked by some botanists as species, and he has entirely omitted several highly polymorphic genera. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-600-400-1859">Under genera, including the most polymorphic forms, Mr. Babington gives 251 species, whereas Mr. Bentham gives only 112,--a difference of 139 doubtful forms! </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-600-500-1859">Amongst animals which unite for each birth, and which are highly locomotive, doubtful forms, ranked by one zoologist as a species and by another as a variety, can rarely be found within the same country, but are common in separated areas. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-600-600-1859">How many of those birds and insects in North America and Europe, which differ very slightly from each other, have been ranked by one eminent naturalist as undoubted species, and by another as varieties, or, as they are often called, as geographical races! </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH2-600-700-1859">Many years ago, when comparing, and seeing others compare, the birds from the separate islands of the Galapagos Archipelago, both one with another, and with those from the American mainland, I was much struck how entirely vague and arbitrary is the distinction between species and varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH2-600-800-1859">On the islets of the little Madeira group there are many insects which are characterized as varieties in Mr. Wollaston's admirable work, but which it cannot  
 <pb id="E-48-1859" corres="S-48-1859" n="48"/>
<pb id="S-49-1859" corres="E-49-1859" n="49"/> <note type="pg"> 49 CHAP. II. DOUBTFUL SPECIES.</note>be doubted would be ranked as distinct species by many entomologists. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH2-600-900-1859">Even Ireland has a few animals, now generally regarded as varieties, but which have been ranked as species by some zoologists.  </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH2-600-1000-1859">Several most experienced ornithologists consider our British red grouse as only a strongly-marked race of a Norwegian species, whereas the greater number rank it as an undoubted species peculiar to Great Britain. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH2-600-1100-1859">A wide distance between the homes of two doubtful forms leads many naturalists to rank both as distinct species; but what distance, it has been well asked, will suffice? </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH2-600-1200-1859">if that between America and Europe is ample, will that between the Continent and the Azores, or Madeira, or the Canaries, or Ireland, be sufficient? </ab>
<ab  n="1300" id="CH2-600-1300-1859">It must be admitted that many forms, considered by highly-competent judges as varieties, have so perfectly the character of species that they are ranked by other highly competent judges as good and true species. </ab>
<ab  n="1400" id="CH2-600-1400-1859">But to discuss whether they are rightly called species or varieties, before any definition of these terms has been generally accepted, is vainly to beat the air. </ab></p>
<p  n="700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-700-100-1859">Many of the cases of strongly-marked varieties or doubtful species well deserve consideration; for several interesting lines of argument, from geographical distribution, analogical variation, hybridism, etc., have been brought to bear on the attempt to determine their rank. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-700-200-1859">I will here give only a single instance,--the well-known one of the primrose and cowslip, or Primula veris and elatior. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-700-300-1859">These plants differ considerably in appearance; they have a different flavour and emit a different odour; they flower at slightly different periods; they grow in somewhat different stations; they ascend mountains to different heights; they have different geographical ranges; and lastly, according to very numerous experiments made during several years by <note type="sg"> D                        </note> 
 <pb id="E-49-1859" corres="S-49-1859" n="49"/>
<pb id="S-50-1859" corres="E-50-1859" n="50"/> <note type="pg"> 50 DOUBTFUL SPECIES. CHAP. II.</note>that most careful observer Gärtner, they can be crossed only with much difficulty. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-700-400-1859">We could hardly wish for better evidence of the two forms being specifically distinct. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-700-500-1859">On the other hand, they are united by many intermediate links, and it is very doubtful whether these links are hybrids; and there is, as it seems to me, an overwhelming amount of experimental evidence, showing that they descend from common parents, and consequently must be ranked as varieties. </ab></p>
<p  n="800">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-800-100-1859">Close investigation, in most cases, will bring naturalists to an agreement how to rank doubtful forms. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-800-200-1859">Yet it must be confessed, that it is in the best-known countries that we find the greatest number of forms of doubtful value. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-800-300-1859">I have been struck with the fact, that if any animal or plant in a state of nature be highly useful to man, or from any cause closely attract his attention, varieties of it will almost universally be found recorded. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-800-400-1859">These varieties, moreover, will be often ranked by some authors as species. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-800-500-1859">Look at the common oak, how closely it has been studied; yet a German author makes more than a dozen species out of forms, which are very generally considered as varieties; and in this country the highest botanical authorities and practical men can be quoted to show that the sessile and pedunculated oaks are either good and distinct species or mere varieties. </ab></p>
<p  n="900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-900-100-1859">When a young naturalist commences the study of a group of organisms quite unknown to him, he is at first much perplexed to determine what differences to consider as specific, and what as varieties; for he knows nothing of the amount and kind of variation to which the group is subject; and this shows, at least, how very generally there is some variation. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-900-200-1859">But if he confine his attention to one class within one country, he will soon make up his mind how to rank most of the doubtful forms. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-900-300-1859">His  
 <pb id="E-50-1859" corres="S-50-1859" n="50"/>
<pb id="S-51-1859" corres="E-51-1859" n="51"/> <note type="pg"> 51 CHAP. II. DOUBTFUL SPECIES.</note>general tendency will be to make many species, for he will become impressed, just like the pigeon or poultry-fancier before alluded to, with the amount of difference in the forms which he is continually studying; and he has little general knowledge of analogical variation in other groups and in other countries, by which to correct his first impressions. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-900-400-1859">As he extends the range of his observations, he will meet with more cases of difficulty; for he will encounter a greater number of closely-allied forms. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-900-500-1859">But if his observations be widely extended, he will in the end generally be enabled to make up his own mind which to call varieties and which species; but he will succeed in this at the expense of admitting much variation,--and the truth of this admission will often be disputed by other naturalists. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-900-600-1859">When, moreover, he comes to study allied forms brought from countries not now continuous, in which case he can hardly hope to find the intermediate links between his doubtful forms, he will have to trust almost entirely to analogy, and his difficulties will rise to a climax. </ab></p>
<p  n="1000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1000-100-1859">Certainly no clear line of demarcation has as yet been drawn between species and sub-species--that is, the forms which in the opinion of some naturalists come very near to, but do not quite arrive at the rank of species; or, again, between sub-species and well-marked varieties, or between lesser varieties and individual differences. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1000-200-1859">These differences blend into each other in an insensible series; and a series impresses the mind with the idea of an actual passage. </ab></p>
<p  n="1100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1100-100-1859">Hence I look at individual differences, though of small interest to the systematist, as of high importance for us, as being the first step towards such slight varieties as are barely thought worth recording in works on natural history. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1100-200-1859">And I look at varieties which are in any degree more distinct and permanent, as steps leading to more <note type="sg"> D 2                       </note> 
 <pb id="E-51-1859" corres="S-51-1859" n="51"/>
<pb id="S-52-1859" corres="E-52-1859" n="52"/> <note type="pg"> 52 VARIETIES GRADUATE INTO SPECIES. CHAP. II.</note>strongly marked and more permanent varieties; and at these latter, as leading to sub-species, and to species. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1100-300-1859">The passage from one stage of difference to another and higher stage may be, in some cases, due merely to the long-continued action of different physical conditions in two different regions; but I have not much faith in this view; and I attribute the passage of a variety, from a state in which it differs very slightly from its parent to one in which it differs more, to the action of natural selection in accumulating (as will hereafter be more fully explained) differences of structure in certain definite directions. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1100-400-1859">Hence I believe a well-marked variety may be justly called an incipient species; but whether this belief be justifiable must be judged of by the general weight of the several facts and views given throughout this work. </ab></p>
<p  n="1200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1200-100-1859">It need not be supposed that all varieties or incipient species necessarily attain the rank of species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1200-200-1859">They may whilst in this incipient state become extinct, or they may endure as varieties for very long periods, as has been shown to be the case by Mr. Wollaston with the varieties of certain fossil land-shells in Madeira. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1200-300-1859">If a variety were to flourish so as to exceed in numbers the parent species, it would then rank as the species, and the species as the variety; or it might come to supplant and exterminate the parent species; or both might co-exist, and both rank as independent species. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1200-400-1859">But we shall hereafter have to return to this subject. </ab></p>
<p  n="1300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1300-100-1859">From these remarks it will be seen that I look at the term species, as one arbitrarily given for the sake of convenience to a set of individuals closely resembling each other, and that it does not essentially differ from the term variety, which is given to less distinct and more fluctuating forms. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1300-200-1859">The term variety, again, in comparison with mere individual differences, is also applied arbitrarily, and for mere convenience sake.  
 <pb id="E-52-1859" corres="S-52-1859" n="52"/>
<pb id="S-53-1859" corres="E-53-1859" n="53"/> <note type="pg"> 53 CHAP. II. DOMINANT SPECIES VARY MOST.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="1400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1400-100-1859">Guided by theoretical considerations, I thought that some interesting results might be obtained in regard to the nature and relations of the species which vary most, by tabulating all the varieties in several well-worked floras. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1400-200-1859">At first this seemed a simple task; but Mr. H. C. Watson, to whom I am much indebted for valuable advice and assistance on this subject, soon convinced me that there were many difficulties, as did subsequently Dr.  Hooker, even in stronger terms. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1400-300-1859">I shall reserve for my future work the discussion of these difficulties, and the tables themselves of the proportional numbers of the varying species. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1400-400-1859">Dr.  Hooker permits me to add, that after having carefully read my manuscript, and examined the tables, he thinks that the following statements are fairly well established. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-1400-500-1859">The whole subject, however, treated as it necessarily here is with much brevity, is rather perplexing, and allusions cannot be avoided to the "struggle for existence," "divergence of character," and other questions, hereafter to be discussed. </ab></p>
<p  n="1500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1500-100-1859">Alph. De Candolle and others have shown that plants which have very wide ranges generally present varieties; and this might have been expected, as they become exposed to diverse physical conditions, and as they come into competition (which, as we shall hereafter see, is a far more important circumstance) with different sets of organic beings. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1500-200-1859">But my tables further show that, in any limited country, the species which are most common, that is abound most in individuals, and the species which are most widely diffused within their own country (and this is a different consideration from wide range, and to a certain extent from commonness), often give rise to varieties sufficiently well-marked to have been recorded in botanical works. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1500-300-1859">Hence it is the most flourishing, or, as they may be called, the dominant species,--  
 <pb id="E-53-1859" corres="S-53-1859" n="53"/>
<pb id="S-54-1859" corres="E-54-1859" n="54"/> <note type="pg"> 54 DOMINANT SPECIES VARY MOSt. CHAP. II.</note>those which range widely over the world, are the most diffused in their own country, and are the most numerous in individuals,--which oftenest produce well-marked varieties, or, as I consider them, incipient species. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1500-400-1859">And this, perhaps, might have been anticipated; for, as varieties, in order to become in any degree permanent, necessarily have to struggle with the other inhabitants of the country, the species which are already dominant will be the most likely to yield offspring which, though in some slight degree modified, will still inherit those advantages that enabled their parents to become dominant over their compatriots. </ab></p>
<p  n="1600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1600-100-1859">If the plants inhabiting a country and described in any Flora be divided into two equal masses, all those in the larger genera being placed on one side, and all those in the smaller genera on the other side, a somewhat larger number of the very common and much diffused or dominant species will be found on the side of the larger genera. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1600-200-1859">This, again, might have been anticipated; for the mere fact of many species of the same genus inhabiting any country, shows that there is something in the organic or inorganic conditions of that country favourable to the genus; and, consequently, we might have expected to have found in the larger genera, or those including many species, a large proportional number of dominant species. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1600-300-1859">But so many causes tend to obscure this result, that I am surprised that my tables show even a small majority on the side of the larger genera. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1600-400-1859">I will here allude to only two causes of obscurity. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-1600-500-1859">Fresh-water and salt-loving plants have generally very wide ranges and are much diffused, but this seems to be connected with the nature of the stations inhabited by them, and has little or no relation to the size of the genera to which the species belong. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-1600-600-1859">Again, plants low in the scale of organisation are  
 <pb id="E-54-1859" corres="S-54-1859" n="54"/>
<pb id="S-55-1859" corres="E-55-1859" n="55"/> <note type="pg"> 55 CHAP. II. SPECIES OF LARGE GENERA
VARIABLE.</note>generally much more widely diffused than plants higher in the scale; and here again there is no close relation to the size of the genera.  </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH2-1600-700-1859">The cause of lowly-organised plants ranging widely will be discussed in our chapter on geographical distribution. </ab></p>
<p  n="1700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1700-100-1859">From looking at species as only strongly-marked and well-defined varieties, I was led to anticipate that the species of the larger genera in each country would oftener present varieties, than the species of the smaller genera; for wherever many closely related species (<hi rend="ital">i</hi> .<hi rend="ital">e</hi> . species of the same genus) have been formed, many varieties or incipient species ought, as a general rule, to be now forming. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1700-200-1859">Where many large trees grow, we expect to find saplings. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1700-300-1859">Where many species of a genus have been formed through variation, circumstances have been favourable for variation; and hence we might expect that the circumstances would generally be still favourable to variation. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1700-400-1859">On the other hand, if we look at each species as a special act of creation, there is no apparent reason why more varieties should occur in a group having many species, than in one having few. </ab></p>
<p  n="1800">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1800-100-1859">To test the truth of this anticipation I have arranged the plants of twelve countries, and the coleopterous insects of two districts, into two nearly equal masses, the species of the larger genera on one side, and those of the smaller genera on the other side, and it has invariably proved to be the case that a larger proportion of the species on the side of the larger genera present varieties, than on the side of the smaller genera. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1800-200-1859">Moreover, the species of the large genera which present any varieties, invariably present a larger average number of varieties than do the species of the small genera. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1800-300-1859">Both these results follow when another division is made, and when all the smallest genera, with from only one to four species, are absolutely excluded from the tables. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1800-400-1859">These  
 <pb id="E-55-1859" corres="S-55-1859" n="55"/>
<pb id="S-56-1859" corres="E-56-1859" n="56"/> <note type="pg"> 56 SPECIES OF LARGE GENERA. CHAP. II.</note>facts are of plain signification on the view that species are only strongly marked and permanent varieties; for wherever many species of the same genus have been formed, or where, if we may use the expression, the manufactory of species has been active, we ought generally to find the manufactory still in action, more especially as we have every reason to believe the process of manufacturing new species to be a slow one. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-1800-500-1859">And this certainly is the case, if varieties be looked at as incipient species; for my tables clearly show as a general rule that, wherever many species of a genus have been formed, the species of that genus present a number of varieties, that is of incipient species, beyond the average. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-1800-600-1859">It is not that all large genera are now varying much, and are thus increasing in the number of their species, or that no small genera are now varying and increasing; for if this had been so, it would have been fatal to my theory; inasmuch as geology plainly tells us that small genera have in the lapse of time often increased greatly in size; and that large genera have often come to their maxima, declined, and disappeared. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH2-1800-700-1859">All that we want to show is, that where many species of a genus have been formed, on an average many are still forming; and this holds good. </ab></p>
<p  n="1900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-1900-100-1859">There are other relations between the species of large genera and their recorded varieties which deserve notice. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-1900-200-1859">We have seen that there is no infallible criterion by which to distinguish species and well-marked varieties; and in those cases in which intermediate links have not been found between doubtful forms, naturalists are compelled to come to a determination by the amount of difference between them, judging by analogy whether or not the amount suffices to raise one or both to the rank of species. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-1900-300-1859">Hence the amount of difference is one very important criterion in settling whether two forms  
 <pb id="E-56-1859" corres="S-56-1859" n="56"/>
<pb id="S-57-1859" corres="E-57-1859" n="57"/> <note type="pg"> 57 CHAP. II. RESEMBLE VARIETIES.</note>should be ranked as species or varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-1900-400-1859">Now Fries has remarked in regard to plants, and Westwood in regard to insects, that in large genera the amount of difference between the species is often exceedingly small. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-1900-500-1859">I have endeavoured to test this numerically by averages, and, as far as my imperfect results go, they always confirm the vieW. I have also consulted some sagacious and most experienced observers, and, after deliberation, they concur in this vieW. In this respect, therefore, the species of the larger genera resemble varieties, more than do the species of the smaller genera. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-1900-600-1859">Or the case may be put in another way, and it may be said, that in the larger genera, in which a number of varieties or incipient species greater than the average are now manufacturing, many of the species already manufactured still to a certain extent resemble varieties, for they differ from each other by a less than usual amount of difference. </ab></p>
<p  n="2000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-2000-100-1859">Moreover, the species of the large genera are related to each other, in the same manner as the varieties of any one species are related to each other. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-2000-200-1859">No naturalist pretends that all the species of a genus are equally distinct from each other; they may generally be divided into sub-genera, or sections, or lesser groups. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-2000-300-1859">As Fries has well remarked, little groups of species are generally clustered like satellites around certain other species. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-2000-400-1859">And what are varieties but groups of forms, unequally related to each other, and clustered round certain forms--that is, round their parent-species? </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-2000-500-1859">Undoubtedly there is one most important point of difference between varieties and species; namely, that the amount of difference between varieties, when compared with each other or with their parent-species, is much less than that between the species of the same genus. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-2000-600-1859">But when we come to discuss the principle, as I call it, of Divergence of Character, <note type="sg"> D
3                       </note> 
 <pb id="E-57-1859" corres="S-57-1859" n="57"/>
<pb id="S-58-1859" corres="E-58-1859" n="58"/> <note type="pg"> 58 SPECIES OF LARGE GENERA. CHAP. II.</note>we shall see how this may be explained, and how the lesser differences between varieties will tend to increase into the greater differences between species. </ab></p>
<p  n="2100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-2100-100-1859">There is one other point which seems to me worth notice. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-2100-200-1859">Varieties generally have much restricted ranges: this statement is indeed scarcely more than a truism, for if a variety were found to have a wider range than that of its supposed parent-species, their denominations ought to be reversed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-2100-300-1859">But there is also reason to believe, that those species which are very closely allied to other species, and in so far resemble varieties, often have much restricted ranges. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-2100-400-1859">For instance, Mr. H. C. Watson has marked for me in the well-sifted London Catalogue of plants (4th edition) 63 plants which are therein ranked as species, but which he considers as so closely allied to other species as to be of doubtful value: these 63 reputed species range on an average over 6.9 of the provinces into which Mr. Watson has divided Great Britain. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-2100-500-1859">Now, in this same catalogue, 53 acknowledged varieties are recorded, and these range over 7.7 provinces; whereas, the species to which these varieties belong range over 14.3 provinces. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH2-2100-600-1859">So that the acknowledged varieties have very nearly the same restricted average range, as have those very closely allied forms, marked for me by Mr. Watson as doubtful species, but which are almost universally ranked by British botanists as good and true species. </ab></p>
<p  n="2300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-2300-100-1859">Finally, then, varieties have the same general characters as species, for they cannot be distinguished from species,--except, firstly, by the discovery of intermediate linking forms, and the occurrence of such links cannot affect the actual characters of the forms which they connect; and except, secondly, by a certain amount of  
 <pb id="E-58-1859" corres="S-58-1859" n="58"/>
<pb id="S-59-1859" corres="E-59-1859" n="59"/> <note type="pg"> 59 CHAP. II. RESEMBLE VARIETIES.</note>difference, for two forms, if differing very little, are generally ranked as varieties, notwithstanding that intermediate linking forms have not been discovered; but the amount of difference considered necessary to give to two forms the rank of species is quite indefinite. In genera having more than the average number of species in any country, the species of these genera have more than the average number of varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-2300-200-1859">In large genera the species are apt to be closely, but unequally, allied together, forming little clusters round certain species. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-2300-300-1859">Species very closely allied to other species apparently have restricted ranges. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-2300-400-1859">In all these several respects the species of large genera present a strong analogy with varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH2-2300-500-1859">And we can clearly understand these analogies, if species have once existed as varieties, and have thus originated: whereas, these analogies are utterly inexplicable if each species has been independently created. </ab></p>
<p  n="2400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH2-2400-100-1859">We have, also, seen that it is the most flourishing and dominant species of the larger genera which on an average vary most; and varieties, as we shall hereafter see, tend to become converted into new and distinct species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH2-2400-200-1859">The larger genera thus tend to become larger; and throughout nature the forms of life which are now dominant tend to become still more dominant by leaving many modified and dominant descendants. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH2-2400-300-1859">But by steps hereafter to be explained, the larger genera also tend to break up into smaller genera. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH2-2400-400-1859">And thus, the forms of life throughout the universe become divided into groups subordinate to groups. </ab></p>
</div>
<pb id="E-59-1859" corres="S-59-1859" n="59"/>
 
 
<pb id="S-60-1859" corres="E-60-1859" n="60"/> <note type="pg"> 60 STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE. CHAP. III.</note>
<div type="chapter"  n="CH3" >
<ab  n="T" id="CH3-T-1859">CHAPTER III. </ab>
<ab  n="ST" id="CH3-ST-1859">STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE. </ab>
<ab  n="SQ" id="CH3-SQ-1859">Bears on natural selection -- The term used in a wide sense -- Geometrical powers of increase -- Rapid increase of naturalised animals and plants -- Nature of the checks to increase -- Competition universal -- Effects of climate -- Protection from the number of individuals -- Complex relations of all animals and plants throughout nature -- Struggle for life most severe between individuals and varieties of the same species; often severe between species of the same genus -- The relation of organism to organism the most important of all relations. </ab>
<p  n="100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-100-100-1859">BEFORE entering on the subject of this chapter, I must make a few preliminary remarks, to show how the struggle for existence bears on Natural Selection. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-100-200-1859">It has been seen in the last chapter that amongst organic beings in a state of nature there is some individual variability; indeed I am not aware that this has ever been disputed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-100-300-1859">It is immaterial for us whether a multitude of doubtful forms be called species or sub-species or varieties; what rank, for instance, the two or three hundred doubtful forms of British plants are entitled to hold, if the existence of any well-marked varieties be admitted. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-100-400-1859">But the mere existence of individual variability and of some few well-marked varieties, though necessary as the foundation for the work, helps us but little in understanding how species arise in nature. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-100-500-1859">How have all those exquisite adaptations of one part of the organisation to another part, and to the conditions of life, and of one distinct organic being to another being, been perfected? </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-100-600-1859">We see these beautiful co-adaptations most plainly in the woodpecker and missletoe; and only a little less plainly in the humblest parasite which clings  
 <pb id="E-60-1859" corres="S-60-1859" n="60"/>
<pb id="S-61-1859" corres="E-61-1859" n="61"/> <note type="pg"> 61 CHAP. III. STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE.</note>to the hairs of a quadruped or feathers of a bird; in the structure of the beetle which dives through the water; in the plumed seed which is wafted by the gentlest breeze; in short, we see beautiful adaptations everywhere and in every part of the organic world. </ab></p>
<p  n="200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-200-100-1859">Again, it may be asked, how is it that varieties, which I have called incipient species, become ultimately converted into good and distinct species, which in most cases obviously differ from each other far more than do the varieties of the same species? </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-200-200-1859">How do those groups of species, which constitute what are called distinct genera, and which differ from each other more than do the species of the same genus, arise? </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-200-300-1859">All these results, as we shall more fully see in the next chapter, follow inevitably from the struggle for life. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-200-400-1859">Owing to this struggle for life, any variation, however slight and from whatever cause proceeding, if it be in any degree profitable to an individual of any species, in its infinitely complex relations to other organic beings and to external nature, will tend to the preservation of that individual, and will generally be inherited by its offspring. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-200-500-1859">The offspring, also, will thus have a better chance of surviving, for, of the many individuals of any species which are periodically born, but a small number can survive. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-200-600-1859">I have called this principle, by which each slight variation, if useful, is preserved, by the term of Natural Selection, in order to mark its relation to man's power of selection. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-200-700-1859">We have seen that man by selection can certainly produce great results, and can adapt organic beings to his own uses, through the accumulation of slight but useful variations, given to him by the hand of Nature. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-200-800-1859">But Natural Selection, as we shall hereafter see, is a power incessantly ready for action, and is as immeasurably superior to man's feeble efforts, as the works of Nature are to those of Art.  
 <pb id="E-61-1859" corres="S-61-1859" n="61"/>
<pb id="S-62-1859" corres="E-62-1859" n="62"/> <note type="pg"> 62 STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE. CHAP. III.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-300-100-1859">We will now discuss in a little more detail the struggle for existence. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-300-200-1859">In my future work this subject shall be treated, as it well deserves, at much greater length. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-300-300-1859">The elder De Candolle and Lyell have largely and philosophically shown that all organic beings are exposed to severe competition. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-300-400-1859">In regard to plants, no one has treated this subject with more spirit and ability than W. Herbert, Dean of Manchester, evidently the result of his great horticultural knowledge. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-300-500-1859">Nothing is easier than to admit in words the truth of the universal struggle for life, or more difficult--at least I have found it so--than constantly to bear this conclusion in mind. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-300-600-1859">Yet unless it be thoroughly engrained in the mind, I am convinced that the whole economy of nature, with every fact on distribution, rarity, abundance, extinction, and variation, will be dimly seen or quite misunderstood. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-300-700-1859">We behold the face of nature bright with gladness, we often see superabundance of food; we do not see, or we forget, that the birds which are idly singing round us mostly live on insects or seeds, and are thus constantly destroying life; or we forget how largely these songsters, or their eggs, or their nestlings, are destroyed by birds and beasts of prey; we do not always bear in mind, that though food may be now superabundant, it is not so at all seasons of each recurring year. </ab></p>
<p  n="400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-400-100-1859">I should premise that I use the term Struggle for Existence in a large and metaphorical sense, including dependence of one being on another, and including (which is more important) not only the life of the individual, but success in leaving progeny. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-400-200-1859">Two canine animals in a time of dearth, may be truly said to struggle with each other which shall get food and live. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-400-300-1859">But a plant on the edge of a desert is said to struggle for life against the drought, though more properly it should be said to be dependent on the moisture. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-400-400-1859">A  
 <pb id="E-62-1859" corres="S-62-1859" n="62"/>
<pb id="S-63-1859" corres="E-63-1859" n="63"/> <note type="pg"> 63 CHAP. III. STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE.</note>plant which annually produces a thousand seeds, of which on an average only one comes to maturity, may be more truly said to struggle with the plants of the same and other kinds which already clothe the ground. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-400-500-1859">The missletoe is dependent on the apple and a few other trees, but can only in a far-fetched sense be said to struggle with these trees, for if too many of these parasites grow on the same tree, it will languish and die. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-400-600-1859">But several seedling missletoes, growing close together on the same branch, may more truly be said to struggle with each other. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-400-700-1859">As the missletoe is disseminated by birds, its existence depends on birds; and it may metaphorically be said to struggle with other fruit-bearing plants, in order to tempt birds to devour and thus disseminate its seeds rather than those of other plants. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-400-800-1859">In these several senses, which pass into each other, I use for convenience sake the general term of struggle for existence. </ab></p>
<p  n="500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-500-100-1859">A struggle for existence inevitably follows from the high rate at which all organic beings tend to increase. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-500-200-1859">Every being, which during its natural lifetime produces several eggs or seeds, must suffer destruction during some period of its life, and during some season or occasional year, otherwise, on the principle of geometrical increase, its numbers would quickly become so inordinately great that no country could support the product. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-500-300-1859">Hence, as more individuals are produced than can possibly survive, there must in every case be a struggle for existence, either one individual with another of the same species, or with the individuals of distinct species, or with the physical conditions of life. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-500-400-1859">It is the doctrine of Malthus applied with manifold force to the whole animal and vegetable kingdoms; for in this case there can be no artificial increase of food, and no prudential restraint from marriage. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-500-500-1859">Although some species may  
 <pb id="E-63-1859" corres="S-63-1859" n="63"/>
<pb id="S-64-1859" corres="E-64-1859" n="64"/> <note type="pg"> 64 HIGH RATE OF INCREASE. CHAP. III.</note>be now increasing, more or less rapidly, in numbers, all cannot do so, for the world would not hold them. </ab></p>
<p  n="600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-600-100-1859">There is no exception to the rule that every organic being naturally increases at so high a rate, that if not destroyed, the earth would soon be covered by the progeny of a single pair. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-600-200-1859">Even slow-breeding man has doubled in twenty-five years, and at this rate, in a few thousand years, there would literally not be standing room for his progeny. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-600-300-1859">Linnaeus has calculated that if an annual plant produced only two seeds--and there is no plant so unproductive as this--and their seedlings next year produced two, and so on, then in twenty years there would be a million plants. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-600-400-1859">The elephant is reckoned to be the slowest breeder of all known animals, and I have taken some pains to estimate its probable minimum rate of natural increase: it will be under the mark to assume that it breeds when thirty years old, and goes on breeding till ninety years old, bringing forth three pair of young in this interval; if this be so, at the end of the fifth century there would be alive fifteen million elephants, descended from the first pair. </ab></p>
<p  n="700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-700-100-1859">But we have better evidence on this subject than mere theoretical calculations, namely, the numerous recorded cases of the astonishingly rapid increase of various animals in a state of nature, when circumstances have been favourable to them during two or three following seasons. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-700-200-1859">Still more striking is the evidence from our domestic animals of many kinds which have run wild in several parts of the world: if the statements of the rate of increase of slow-breeding cattle and horses in South-America, and latterly in Australia, had not been well authenticated, they would have been quite incredible. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-700-300-1859">So it is with plants: cases could be given of introduced plants which have become common throughout whole islands in a period of less than ten years. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-700-400-1859">Several  
 <pb id="E-64-1859" corres="S-64-1859" n="64"/>
<pb id="S-65-1859" corres="E-65-1859" n="65"/> <note type="pg"> 65 CHAP. III. HIGH RATE OF INCREASE.</note>of the plants now most numerous over the wide plains of La Plata, clothing square leagues of surface almost to the exclusion of all other plants, have been introduced from Europe; and there are plants which now range in India, as I hear from Dr. Falconer, from Cape Comorin to the Himalaya, which have been imported from America since its discovery. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-700-500-1859">In such cases, and endless instances could be given, no one supposes that the fertility of these animals or plants has been suddenly and temporarily increased in any sensible degree. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-700-600-1859">The obvious explanation is that the conditions of life have been very favourable, and that there has consequently been less destruction of the old and young, and that nearly all the young have been enabled to breed. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-700-700-1859">In such cases the geometrical ratio of increase, the result of which never fails to be surprising, simply explains the extraordinarily rapid increase and wide diffusion of naturalised productions in their new homes. </ab></p>
<p  n="800">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-800-100-1859">In a state of nature almost every plant produces seed, and amongst animals there are very few which do not annually pair. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-800-200-1859">Hence we may confidently assert, that all plants and animals are tending to increase at a geometrical ratio, that all would most rapidly stock every station in which they could any how exist, and that the geometrical tendency to increase must be checked by destruction at some period of life. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-800-300-1859">Our familiarity with the larger domestic animals tends, I think, to mislead us: we see no great destruction falling on them, and we forget that thousands are annually slaughtered for food, and that in a state of nature an equal number would have somehow to be disposed of. </ab></p>
<p  n="900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-900-100-1859">The only difference between organisms which annually produce eggs or seeds by the thousand, and those which produce extremely few, is, that the slow-breeders would require a few more years to people, under favourable  
 <pb id="E-65-1859" corres="S-65-1859" n="65"/>
<pb id="S-66-1859" corres="E-66-1859" n="66"/> <note type="pg"> 66</note><note type="rh"> HIGH RATE OF INCREASE. III.</note>conditions, a whole district, let it be ever so large. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-900-200-1859">The condor lays a couple of eggs and the ostrich a score, and yet in the same country the condor may be the more numerous of the two: the Fulmar petrel lays but one egg, yet it is believed to be the most numerous bird in the world. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-900-300-1859">One fly deposits hundreds of eggs, and another, like the hippobosca, a single one; but this difference does not determine how many individuals of the two species can be supported in a district. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-900-400-1859">A large number of eggs is of some importance to those species, which depend on a rapidly fluctuating amount of food, for it allows them rapidly to increase in number. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-900-500-1859">But the real importance of a large number of eggs or seeds is to make up for much destruction at some period of life; and this period in the great majority of cases is an early one. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-900-600-1859">If an animal can in any way protect its own eggs or young, a small number may be produced, and yet the average stock be fully kept up; but if many eggs or young are destroyed, many must be produced, or the species will become extinct. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-900-700-1859">It would suffice to keep up the full number of a tree, which lived on an average for a thousand years, if a single seed were produced once in a thousand years, supposing that this seed were never destroyed, and could be ensured to germinate in a fitting place. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-900-800-1859">So that in all cases, the average number of any animal or plant depends only indirectly on the number of its eggs or seeds. </ab></p>
<p  n="1000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1000-100-1859">In looking at Nature, it is most necessary to keep the foregoing considerations always in mind--never to forget that every single organic being around us may be said to be striving to the utmost to increase in numbers; that each lives by a struggle at some period of its life; that heavy destruction inevitably falls either on the young or old, during each generation or at recurrent intervals. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1000-200-1859">Lighten any check, mitigate the  
 <pb id="E-66-1859" corres="S-66-1859" n="66"/>
<pb id="S-67-1859" corres="E-67-1859" n="67"/> <note type="sg"> 67</note> <note type="rh"> CHAP. III. CHECKS TO INCREASE.</note>destruction ever so little, and the number of the species will almost instantaneously increase to any amount. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1000-300-1859">The face of Nature may be compared to a yielding surface, with ten thousand sharp wedges packed close together and driven inwards by incessant blows, sometimes one wedge being struck, and then another with greater force. </ab></p>
<p  n="1100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1100-100-1859">What checks the natural tendency of each species to increase in number is most obscure. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1100-200-1859">Look at the most vigorous species; by as much as it swarms in numbers, by so much will its tendency to increase be still further increased. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1100-300-1859">We know not exactly what the checks are in even one single instance. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1100-400-1859">Nor will this surprise any one who reflects how ignorant we are on this head, even in regard to mankind, so incomparably better known than any other animal. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-1100-500-1859">This subject has been ably treated by several authors, and I shall, in my future work, discuss some of the checks at considerable length, more especially in regard to the feral animals of South America. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-1100-600-1859">Here I will make only a few remarks, just to recall to the reader's mind some of the chief points. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-1100-700-1859">Eggs or very young animals seem generally to suffer most, but this is not invariably the case. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-1100-800-1859">With plants there is a vast destruction of seeds, but, from some observations which I have made, I believe that it is the seedlings which suffer most from germinating in ground already thickly stocked with other plants. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH3-1100-900-1859">Seedlings, also, are destroyed in vast numbers by various enemies; for instance, on a piece of ground three feet long and two wide, dug and cleared, and where there could be no choking from other plants, I marked all the seedlings of our native weeds as they came up, and out of the 357 no less than 295 were destroyed, chiefly by slugs and insects. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH3-1100-1000-1859">If turf which has long been mown, and the case would be the same with turf closely browsed by quadrupeds, be let to grow,  
 <pb id="E-67-1859" corres="S-67-1859" n="67"/>
<pb id="S-68-1859" corres="E-68-1859" n="68"/> <note type="sg"> 68</note> <note type="rh"> CHECKS TO INCREASE. CHAP. III.</note>the more vigorous plants gradually kill the less vigorous, though fully grown, plants: thus out of twenty species growing on a little plot of turf (three feet by four) nine species perished from the other species being allowed to grow up freely. </ab></p>
<p  n="1200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1200-100-1859">The amount of food for each species of course gives the extreme limit to which each can increase; but very frequently it is not the obtaining food, but the serving as prey to other animals, which determines the average numbers of a species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1200-200-1859">Thus, there seems to be little doubt that the stock of partridges, grouse, and hares on any large estate depends chiefly on the destruction of vermin. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1200-300-1859">If not one head of game were shot during the next twenty years in England, and, at the same time, if no vermin were destroyed, there would, in all probability, be less game than at present, although hundreds of thousands of game animals are now annually killed. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1200-400-1859">On the other hand, in some cases, as with the elephant and rhinoceros, none are destroyed by beasts of prey: even the tiger in India most rarely dares to attack a young elephant protected by its dam. </ab></p>
<p  n="1300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1300-100-1859">Climate plays an important part in determining the average numbers of a species, and periodical seasons of extreme cold or drought, I believe to be the most effective of all checks. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1300-200-1859">I estimated that the winter of 1854-55 destroyed four-fifths of the birds in my own grounds; and this is a tremendous destruction, when we remember that ten per cent. is an extraordinarily severe mortality from epidemics with man. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1300-300-1859">The action of climate seems at first sight to be quite independent of the struggle for existence; but in so far as climate chiefly acts in reducing food, it brings on the most severe struggle between the individuals, whether of the same or of distinct species, which subsist on the same kind of food. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1300-400-1859">Even when climate, for instance extreme  
 <pb id="E-68-1859" corres="S-68-1859" n="68"/>
<pb id="S-69-1859" corres="E-69-1859" n="69"/> <note type="sg"> 69</note> <note type="rh"> 69 CHAP. III. CHECKS TO INCREASE.</note>cold, acts directly, it will be the least vigorous, or those which have got least food through the advancing winter, which will suffer most. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-1300-500-1859">When we travel from south to north, or from a damp region to a dry, we invariably see some species gradually getting rarer and rarer, and finally disappearing; and the change of climate being conspicuous, we are tempted to attribute the whole effect to its direct action. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-1300-600-1859">But this is a very false view: we forget that each species, even where it most abounds, is constantly suffering enormous destruction at some period of its life, from enemies or from competitors for the same place and food; and if these enemies or competitors be in the least degree favoured by any slight change of climate, they will increase in numbers, and, as each area is already fully stocked with inhabitants, the other species will decrease. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-1300-700-1859">When we travel southward and see a species decreasing in numbers, we may feel sure that the cause lies quite as much in other species being favoured, as in this one being hurt. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-1300-800-1859">So it is when we travel northward, but in a somewhat lesser degree, for the number of species of all kinds, and therefore of competitors, decreases northwards; hence in going northward, or in ascending a mountain, we far oftener meet with stunted forms, due to the <hi rend="ital">directly</hi>  injurious action of climate, than we do in proceeding southwards or in descending a mountain. </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH3-1300-900-1859">When we reach the Arctic regions, or snow-capped summits, or absolute deserts, the struggle for life is almost exclusively with the elements. </ab></p>
<p  n="1400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1400-100-1859">That climate acts in main part indirectly by favouring other species, we may clearly see in the prodigious number of plants in our gardens which can perfectly well endure our climate, but which never become naturalised, for they cannot compete with our native plants, nor resist destruction by our native animals.  
 <pb id="E-69-1859" corres="S-69-1859" n="69"/>
<pb id="S-70-1859" corres="E-70-1859" n="70"/> <note type="sg"> 70</note> <note type="rh"> 70 CHECKS TO INCREASE. CHAP. III.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="1500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1500-100-1859">When a species, owing to highly favourable circumstances, increases inordinately in numbers in a small tract, epidemics--at least, this seems generally to occur with our game animals--often ensue: and here we have a limiting check independent of the struggle for life. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1500-200-1859">But even some of these so-called epidemics appear to be due to parasitic worms, which have from some cause, possibly in part through facility of diffusion amongst the crowded animals, been disproportionably favoured: and here comes in a sort of struggle between the parasite and its prey. </ab></p>
<p  n="1600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1600-100-1859">On the other hand, in many cases, a large stock of individuals of the same species, relatively to the numbers of its enemies, is absolutely necessary for its preservation. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1600-200-1859">Thus we can easily raise plenty of corn and rape-seed, etc., in our fields, because the seeds are in great excess compared with the number of birds which feed on them; nor can the birds, though having a superabundance of food at this one season, increase in number proportionally to the supply of seed, as their numbers are checked during winter: but any one who has tried, knows how troublesome it is to get seed from a few wheat or other such plants in a garden; I have in this case lost every single seed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1600-300-1859">This view of the necessity of a large stock of the same species for its preservation, explains, I believe, some singular facts in nature, such as that of very rare plants being sometimes extremely abundant in the few spots where they do occur; and that of some social plants being social, that is, abounding in individuals, even on the extreme confines of their range. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1600-400-1859">For in such cases, we may believe, that a plant could exist only where the conditions of its life were so favourable that many could exist together, and thus save each other from utter destruction. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-1600-500-1859">I should add that the good effects of frequent intercrossing, and the ill effects  
 <pb id="E-70-1859" corres="S-70-1859" n="70"/>
<pb id="S-71-1859" corres="E-71-1859" n="71"/> <note type="sg"> 71</note> <note type="rh"> 71 CHAP. III. MUTUAL CHECKS TO INCREASE.</note>of close interbreeding, probably come into play in some of these cases; but on this intricate subject I will not here enlarge. </ab></p>
<p  n="1700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1700-100-1859">Many cases are on record showing how complex and unexpected are the checks and relations between organic beings, which have to struggle together in the same country. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1700-200-1859">I will give only a single instance, which, though a simple one, has interested me. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1700-300-1859">In Staffordshire, on the estate of a relation where I had ample means of investigation, there was a large and extremely barren heath, which had never been touched by the hand of man; but several hundred acres of exactly the same nature had been enclosed twenty-five years previously and planted with Scotch fir. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1700-400-1859">The change in the native vegetation of the planted part of the heath was most remarkable, more than is generally seen in passing from one quite different soil to another: not only the proportional numbers of the heath-plants were wholly changed, but twelve species of plants (not counting grasses and carices) flourished in the plantations, which could not be found on the heath. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-1700-500-1859">The effect on the insects must have been still greater, for six insectivorous birds were very common in the plantations, which were not to be seen on the heath; and the heath was frequented by two or three distinct insectivorous birds. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-1700-600-1859">Here we see how potent has been the effect of the introduction of a single tree, nothing whatever else having been done, with the exception that the land had been enclosed, so that cattle could not enter. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-1700-700-1859">But how important an element enclosure is, I plainly saw near Farnham, in Surrey. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-1700-800-1859">Here there are extensive heaths, with a few clumps of old Scotch firs on the distant hill-tops: within the last ten years large spaces have been enclosed, and self-sown firs are now springing up in multitudes, so close together that all cannot live.  
 <pb id="E-71-1859" corres="S-71-1859" n="71"/>
<pb id="S-72-1859" corres="E-72-1859" n="72"/> <note type="sg"> 72</note> <note type="rh"> 72 MUTUAL CHECKS TO INCREASE. CHAP. III.</note></ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH3-1700-900-1859">When I ascertained that these young trees had not been sown or planted, I was so much surprised at their numbers that I went to several points of view, whence I could examine hundreds of acres of the unenclosed heath, and literally I could not see a single Scotch fir, except the old planted clumps. </ab>
<ab  n="1000" id="CH3-1700-1000-1859">But on looking closely between the stems of the heath, I found a multitude of seedlings and little trees, which had been perpetually browsed down by the cattle. </ab>
<ab  n="1100" id="CH3-1700-1100-1859">In one square yard, at a point some hundred yards distant from one of the old clumps, I counted thirty-two little trees; and one of them, judging from the rings of growth, had during twenty-six years tried to raise its head above the stems of the heath, and had failed. </ab>
<ab  n="1200" id="CH3-1700-1200-1859">No wonder that, as soon as the land was enclosed, it became thickly clothed with vigorously growing young firs. </ab>
<ab  n="1300" id="CH3-1700-1300-1859">Yet the heath was so extremely barren and so extensive that no one would ever have imagined that cattle would have so closely and effectually searched it for food. </ab></p>
<p  n="1800">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1800-100-1859">Here we see that cattle absolutely determine the existence of the Scotch fir; but in several parts of the world insects determine the existence of cattle. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1800-200-1859">Perhaps Paraguay offers the most curious instance of this; for here neither cattle nor horses nor dogs have ever run wild, though they swarm southward and northward in a feral state; and Azara and Rengger have shown that this is caused by the greater number in Paraguay of a certain fly, which lays its eggs in the navels of these animals when first born. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1800-300-1859">The increase of these flies, numerous as they are, must be habitually checked by some means, probably by birds. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1800-400-1859">Hence, if certain insectivorous birds (whose numbers are probably regulated by hawks or beasts of prey) were to increase in Paraguay, the flies would decrease--then cattle and horses would become feral, and this would certainly greatly alter (as  
 <pb id="E-72-1859" corres="S-72-1859" n="72"/>
<pb id="S-73-1859" corres="E-73-1859" n="73"/> <note type="pg"> 73</note> <note type="rh"> 73 CHAP. III. MUTUAL CHECKS TO INCREASE.</note>indeed I have observed in parts of South America) the vegetation: this again would largely affect the insects; and this, as we just have seen in Staffordshire, the insectivorous birds, and so onwards in ever-increasing circles of complexity. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-1800-500-1859">We began this series by insectivorous birds, and we have ended with them. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-1800-600-1859">Not that in nature the relations can ever be as simple as this. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-1800-700-1859">Battle within battle must ever be recurring with varying success; and yet in the long-run the forces are so nicely balanced, that the face of nature remains uniform for long periods of time, though assuredly the merest trifle would often give the victory to one organic being over another. </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-1800-800-1859">Nevertheless so profound is our ignorance, and so high our presumption, that we marvel when we hear of the extinction of an organic being; and as we do not see the cause, we invoke cataclysms to desolate the world, or invent laws on the duration of the forms of life! </ab></p>
<p  n="1900">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-1900-100-1859">I am tempted to give one more instance showing how plants and animals, most remote in the scale of nature, are bound together by a web of complex relations. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-1900-200-1859">I shall hereafter have occasion to show that the exotic Lobelia fulgens, in this part of England, is never visited by insects, and consequently, from its peculiar structure, never can set a seed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-1900-300-1859">Many of our orchidaceous plants absolutely require the visits of moths to remove their pollen-masses and thus to fertilise them. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-1900-400-1859">I have, also, reason to believe that humble-bees are indispensable to the fertilisation of the heartsease (Viola tricolor), for other bees do not visit this flower. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-1900-500-1859">From experiments which I have tried, I have found that the visits of bees, if not indispensable, are at least highly beneficial to the fertilisation of our clovers; but humble-bees alone visit the common red clover (Trifolium pratense), as other bees cannot reach the nectar. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-1900-600-1859">Hence I have very little doubt, that if the whole genus of humble-bees became <note type="sg"> E                          </note> 
 <pb id="E-73-1859" corres="S-73-1859" n="73"/>
<pb id="S-74-1859" corres="E-74-1859" n="74"/> <note type="pg"> 74</note> <note type="rh"> 74 MUTUAL CHECKS TO INCREASE. CHAP. III.</note>extinct or very rare in England, the heartsease and red clover would become very rare, or wholly disappear. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-1900-700-1859">The number of humble-bees in any district depends in a great degree on the number of field-mice, which destroy their combs and nests; and Mr. H. Newman, who has long attended to the habits of humble-bees, believes that "more than two thirds of them are thus destroyed all over England." </ab>
<ab  n="800" id="CH3-1900-800-1859">Now the number of mice is largely dependent, as every one knows, on the number of cats; and Mr. Newman says, "Near villages and small towns I have found the nests of humble-bees more numerous than elsewhere, which I attribute to the number of cats that destroy the mice." </ab>
<ab  n="900" id="CH3-1900-900-1859">Hence it is quite credible that the presence of a feline animal in large numbers in a district might determine, through the intervention first of mice and then of bees, the frequency of certain flowers in that district! </ab></p>
<p  n="2000">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2000-100-1859">In the case of every species, many different checks, acting at different periods of life, and during different seasons or years, probably come into play; some one check or some few being generally the most potent, but all concurring in determining the average number or even the existence of the species. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2000-200-1859">In some cases it can be shown that widely-different checks act on the same species in different districts. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-2000-300-1859">When we look at the plants and bushes clothing an entangled bank, we are tempted to attribute their proportional numbers and kinds to what we call chance. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-2000-400-1859">But how false a view is this! </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-2000-500-1859">Every one has heard that when an American forest is cut down, a very different vegetation springs up; but it has been observed that the trees now growing on the ancient Indian mounds, in the Southern United States, display the same beautiful diversity and proportion of kinds as in the surrounding virgin forests. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-2000-600-1859">What a struggle between the several kinds of trees  
 <pb id="E-74-1859" corres="S-74-1859" n="74"/>
<pb id="S-75-1859" corres="E-75-1859" n="75"/> <note type="pg"> 75</note> <note type="rh"> 75 CHAP. III. MUTUAL CHECKS TO INCREASE.</note>must here have gone on during long centuries, each annually scattering its seeds by the thousand; what war between insect and insect--between insects, snails, and other animals with birds and beasts of prey--all striving to increase, and all feeding on each other or on the trees or their seeds and seedlings, or on the other plants which first clothed the ground and thus checked the growth of the trees! </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-2000-700-1859">Throw up a handful of feathers, and all must fall to the ground according to definite laws; but how simple is this problem compared to the action and reaction of the innumerable plants and animals which have determined, in the course of centuries, the proportional numbers and kinds of trees now growing on the old Indian ruins! </ab></p>
<p  n="2100">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2100-100-1859">The dependency of one organic being on another, as of a parasite on its prey, lies generally between beings remote in the scale of nature. This is often the case with those which may strictly be said to struggle with each other for existence, as in the case of locusts and grass-feeding quadrupeds. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2100-200-1859">But the struggle almost invariably will be most severe between the individuals of the same species, for they frequent the same districts, require the same food, and are exposed to the same dangers. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-2100-300-1859">In the case of varieties of the same species, the struggle will generally be almost equally severe, and we sometimes see the contest soon decided: for instance, if several varieties of wheat be sown together, and the mixed seed be resown, some of the varieties which best suit the soil or climate, or are naturally the most fertile, will beat the others and so yield more seed, and will consequently in a few years quite supplant the other varieties. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-2100-400-1859">To keep up a mixed stock of even such extremely close varieties as the variously coloured sweet-peas, they must be each year harvested separately, and the seed then mixed in due propor- <note type="sg"> E
2                      </note> 
 <pb id="E-75-1859" corres="S-75-1859" n="75"/>
<pb id="S-76-1859" corres="E-76-1859" n="76"/> <note type="pg"> 76</note> <note type="rh"> 76 STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE. CHAP. III.</note>tion, otherwise the weaker kinds will steadily decrease in numbers and disappear. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-2100-500-1859">So again with the varieties of sheep: it has been asserted that certain mountain-varieties will starve out other mountain-varieties, so that they cannot be kept together. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-2100-600-1859">The same result has followed from keeping together different varieties of the medicinal leech. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-2100-700-1859">It may even be doubted whether the varieties of any one of our domestic plants or animals have so exactly the same strength, habits, and constitution, that the original proportions of a mixed stock could be kept up for half a dozen generations, if they were allowed to struggle together, like beings in a state of nature, and if the seed or young were not annually sorted. </ab></p>
<p  n="2200">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2200-100-1859">As species of the same genus have usually, though by no means invariably, some similarity in habits and constitution, and always in structure, the struggle will generally be more severe between species of the same genus, when they come into competition with each other, than between species of distinct genera. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2200-200-1859">We see this in the recent extension over parts of the United States of one species of swallow having caused the decrease of another species. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-2200-300-1859">The recent increase of the missel-thrush in parts of Scotland has caused the decrease of the song-thrush. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-2200-400-1859">How frequently we hear of one species of rat taking the place of another species under the most different climates!  </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-2200-500-1859">In Russia the small Asiatic cockroach has everywhere driven before it its great congener. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-2200-600-1859">One species of charlock will supplant another, and so in other cases. </ab>
<ab  n="700" id="CH3-2200-700-1859">We can dimly see why the competition should be most severe between allied forms, which fill nearly the same place in the economy of nature; but probably in no one case could we precisely say why one species has been victorious over another in the great battle of life.  
 <pb id="E-76-1859" corres="S-76-1859" n="76"/>
<pb id="S-77-1859" corres="E-77-1859" n="77"/> <note type="pg"> 77</note> <note type="rh"> 77 CHAP. III. STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE.</note></ab></p>
<p  n="2300">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2300-100-1859">A corollary of the highest importance may be deduced from the foregoing remarks, namely, that the structure of every organic being is related, in the most essential yet often hidden manner, to that of all other organic beings, with which it comes into competition for food or residence, or from which it has to escape, or on which it preys. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2300-200-1859">This is obvious in the structure of the teeth and talons of the tiger; and in that of the legs and claws of the parasite which clings to the hair on the tiger's body. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-2300-300-1859">But in the beautifully plumed seed of the dandelion, and in the flattened and fringed legs of the water-beetle, the relation seems at first confined to the elements of air and water. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-2300-400-1859">Yet the advantage of plumed seeds no doubt stands in the closest relation to the land being already thickly clothed by other plants; so that the seeds may be widely distributed and fall on unoccupied ground. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-2300-500-1859">In the water-beetle, the structure of its legs, so well adapted for diving, allows it to compete with other aquatic insects, to hunt for its own prey, and to escape serving as prey to other animals. </ab></p>
<p  n="2400">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2400-100-1859">The store of nutriment laid up within the seeds of many plants seems at first sight to have no sort of relation to other plants. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2400-200-1859">But from the strong growth of young plants produced from such seeds (as peas and beans), when sown in the midst of long grass, I suspect that the chief use of the nutriment in the seed is to favour the growth of the young seedling, whilst struggling with other plants growing vigorously all around. </ab></p>
<p  n="2500">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2500-100-1859">Look at a plant in the midst of its range, why does it not double or quadruple its numbers? </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2500-200-1859">We know that it can perfectly well withstand a little more heat or cold, dampness or dryness, for elsewhere it ranges  
 <pb id="E-77-1859" corres="S-77-1859" n="77"/>
<pb id="S-78-1859" corres="E-78-1859" n="78"/> <note type="pg"> 78</note> <note type="rh"> 78 STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE. CHAP. III.</note>into slightly hotter or colder, damper or drier districts. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-2500-300-1859">In this case we can clearly see that if we wished in imagination to give the plant the power of increasing in number, we should have to give it some advantage over its competitors, or over the animals which preyed on it. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-2500-400-1859">On the confines of its geographical range, a change of constitution with respect to climate would clearly be an advantage to our plant; but we have reason to believe that only a few plants or animals range so far, that they are destroyed by the rigour of the climate alone. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-2500-500-1859">Not until we reach the extreme confines of life, in the arctic regions or on the borders of an utter desert, will competition cease. </ab>
<ab  n="600" id="CH3-2500-600-1859">The land may be extremely cold or dry, yet there will be competition between some few species, or between the individuals of the same species, for the warmest or dampest spots. </ab></p>
<p  n="2600">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2600-100-1859">Hence, also, we can see that when a plant or animal is placed in a new country amongst new competitors, though the climate may be exactly the same as in its former home, yet the conditions of its life will generally be changed in an essential manner. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2600-200-1859">If we wished to increase its average numbers in its new home, we should have to modify it in a different way to what we should have done in its native country; for we should have to give it some advantage over a different set of competitors or enemies. </ab></p>
<p  n="2700">
<ab  n="100" id="CH3-2700-100-1859">It is good thus to try in our imagination to give any form some advantage over another. </ab>
<ab  n="200" id="CH3-2700-200-1859">Probably in no single instance should we know what to do, so as to succeed. </ab>
<ab  n="300" id="CH3-2700-300-1859">It will convince us of our ignorance on the mutual relations of all organic beings; a conviction as necessary, as it seems to be difficult to acquire. </ab>
<ab  n="400" id="CH3-2700-400-1859">All that we can do, is to keep steadily in mind that each organic being is striving to increase at a geometrical  
 <pb id="E-78-1859" corres="S-78-1859" n="78"/>
<pb id="S-79-1859" corres="E-79-1859" n="79"/> <note type="pg"> 79</note> <note type="rh"> 79 CHAP. III. STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE.</note>ratio; that each at some period of its life, during some season of the year, during each generation or at intervals, has to struggle for life, and to suffer great destruction. </ab>
<ab  n="500" id="CH3-2700-500-1859">When we reflect on this struggle, we may console ourselves with the full belief, that the war of nature is not incessant, that no fear is felt, that death is generally prompt, and that the vigorous, the healthy, and the happy survive and multiply.</ab></p>
</div>
<pb id="E-79-1859" corres="S-79-1859" n="79"/>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>